<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Rav Weinfeld</title>
    <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Rav Weinfeld</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Korach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Motivation for Machlokes The Parsha begins ויקח קרח בן יצהר בן קהת בן לוי ודתן ואבירם בני אליאב ואון בן פלת בני ראובן. This coalition was made up of a group of individuals who were all seeking different things, some the נשיאות and some the כהונה. Although און בן פלת didn’t really have a claim, it could be that he was the man behind the ideological טענה of כל העדה כלם קדשים ובתוכם יקוק ומדוע תתנשאו על קהל ה&#39;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shelach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Wise and Righteous The Parsha begins שלח לך אנשים. Rashi on the words כלם אנשים says כל אנשים שבמקרא לשון חשיבות ואותה שעה כשרים היו meaning they were Tzadikim. The Targum Yonason Ben Uziel says on the word אנשים that they were חריפין-sharp/astute people. Lastly, the Ibn Ezra says on the word אנשים that they were גבורים. So it would appear that everyone agrees that אנשים is a לשון of חשובים but there are three ways in explaining in what their חשיבות was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaloscha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</guid>
      <description>5781 Opportunity When Out of Place The Parsha begins with Ahron being commanded בהעלתך את הנרת. Rashi points out that this Parshas is out of place by asking למה נסמכה פרשת המנורה לפרשת הנשיאים because if these events occurred chronologically, then there would be no need for such a question. Therefore, the fact that Rashi asks למה נסמכה indicates that this event is not in the chronological order of event as we see in the Gemara in Gittin on 60b that the Parshah of the Menorah was one of the eight Parshiyos given on Rosh Chodesh Nissan before the Nesiim began to bring their Korbanos and it wasn’t said now, after the Nesiim concluded bringing their Korbanos, which was on the twelfth day of Nissan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naso</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</guid>
      <description>5781 Importance of personal connection The second half of the Parsha discusses the Korbanos that were brought by the Nesiim by the Chanukas Hamishkan. Although the Nesiim brought identical Korbanos, the Torah spells out the Korbanos that each Nasi brought. It would seem to make more sense for the Torah to write it once and then say that this is what each Nasi brought. What is the significance and message being taught that the Korbanos of each Nasi is written out even though it is seemingly repetitious as they are all identical?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bamidbar</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Great Scribe and Counter The Kiddush was sponsored by the Schreiber family in honor of the birth of a baby girl.
The word Schreiber is very much connected to Parshas Bamidbar because Shcreiber means “writer”. The Gemara in Sotah 13b refers to Moshe Rabbeinu as the ספרא רבה דישראל, which simply means the great scribe of Yisrael. Why is Moshe Rabbeinu called the great scribe of Yisrael?
The Maharsha there is bothered why Moshe is called the ספרא רבה דישראל, specifically the great scribe of the Jews if the writing of the Torah was on behalf of Hashem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behar Bechukosai</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beharbechukosai/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beharbechukosai/</guid>
      <description>5781 Meron Tragedy In connection with the terrible tragedy that happened in Meron where so many young people, each one special in his own way, were plucked from us in such a quick and cruel way. People have been searching for meaning and therefore we should start with the simple and basic meaning of all this.
The Rav began with a story he heard from his Rebbe Reb Berel Soloveitchik. Reb Chaim Brisker had three sons and the least known was Reb Yisrael Gershon who was a bit eccentric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emor</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</guid>
      <description>5781 כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו גדול הימנו The Parsha begins with the many mitzvos that apply only to Kohanim. The Gemara in Yevamos 5a says שאני כהנים הואיל וריבה בהן הכתוב מצות יתירות that Kohanim are unique in the sense that they have many more Mitzvos that only apply to them.
One could ask why is it that the Kohanim specifically are the people who have more Mitzvos than other Jews.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lag Baomer</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acharei Kedoshim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/achareikedoshim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/achareikedoshim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Mourning Loss in the Link Parshas Acharei begins immediately following the death of Aarons two sons, נדב ואביהו as the Pasuk says וידבר ה&#39; אל משה אחרי מות שני בני אהרן. The באר היטב in אורח חיים סימן תרכ&amp;quot;א brings in the name of the Zohar and the Arizal that when the Psukim discussing the death of Aarons sons is being read on Yom Kippur, יש להצטער על מיתתן ולהוריד עליהם דמעות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tazria Metzorah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazraimetzorah/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazraimetzorah/</guid>
      <description>5781 The טומאה of a יולדת Parshas Tazria begins with טומאת יולדת. Regarding her טומאה state, the Pasuk says בכל קדש לא תגע and Rashi writes לרבות את התרומה, לפי שזו טבולת יום ארוך, שטבלה לסוף שבעה ואין שמשה מעריב לטהרה עד שקיעת החמה של יום ארבעים, שלמחר תביא את כפרת טהרתה. A יולדת has a status of a טבול יום ארוך because she remains a טבול יום either for 33 days or 66 days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemini</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pesach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</guid>
      <description>Videos Krias Yam Suf 5781 
Inyanei Haggadah 
The Order on the Seder Night 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayikra</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781 
Language of Affection 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayakhel Pekudei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhelpekudei/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhelpekudei/</guid>
      <description>5781 Pleasantness Throughout The Week וירא משה את כל המלאכה והנה עשו אתה כאשר צוה יקוק כן עשו ויברך אתם משה (לט,מג)
Rashi explains אמר להם יהי רצון שתשרה שכינה במעשה ידיכם, (תהלים צ יז) ויהי נועם ה&#39; אלהינו עלינו ומעשה ידינו וגו. Moshe Rabbeinu gave a Brachah that the Shechina should reside in the Mishkan. The Pasuk says that the Mishkan was erected on Rosh Chodesh Nissan and the Gemara in Shabbos 87b says that day was the first day of the week-ראשון למעשה בראשית.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Sisa</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</guid>
      <description>5780 Hold On This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by Reb Yisrael Neuberger in honor of his new book “Hold On”. (On the cover, there is a rope so the Rav digressed on the idea of a חבל.)
The word חבל not only means a rope but at times is used to describe a גרל as the Pasuk says in Haazinu כי חלק יקוק עמו יעקב חבל נחלתו( לב,ט). Now if every creation and creature in this world has a specific purpose as it says לא ברא הקב&amp;quot;ה דבר אחד לבטלה (במ&amp;quot;ר יח,יח, זהר א כג), then all the more so, the human being which is created בצלם אלוקים for sure has a purpose and a mission that only he can fulfil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</guid>
      <description>5780 Haman thought that Adar was a month of bad luck for the Jews because of the death of Moshe and it was probably a painful and difficult day for the Jews being that they lost the greatest leader in history. But the Jews pulled it together and on that day they learned a very important lesson. They learned that as a people we must keep moving on and with the death comes a new beginning and opportunity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terumah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</guid>
      <description>5781 Shabbos Zachor The Kiddush was sponsored by Reb Shalom Huss in memory of his father. Once a person continues on to the next world, he is no longer able to do Mitzvos and reach higher levels, he is no longer a מהלך. However, the living are able to make a Brachah לעילוי נשמתו and it can affect the נשמה. The Gemara says about a son ברא כרעיה דאבוה that a son is like a leg of his father which can be understood to mean that one’s father can continue walking through the Mitzvos that his son performs in this world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mishpatim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Emphasis of Mishpatim The Parsha begins ואלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם. Rashi says:
אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה לא תעלה על דעתך לומר אשנה להם הפרק וההלכה ב&#39; או ג&#39; פעמים עד שתהא סדורה בפיהם כמשנתה, ואיני מטריח עצמי להבינם טעמי הדבר ופירושו, לכך נאמר אשר תשים לפניהם, כשלחן הערוך ומוכן לאכול לפני האדם.
Hashem told Moshe that he shouldn’t just teach Klal Yisrael the Torah a few times until they are well versed and not explain the טעמי המצות rather he should teach them with their טעמים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yisro</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</guid>
      <description>5781 A Torah For All In this week’s Parsha, the Jewish people received the Torah at Har Sinai. The revelation at Sinai was a very exclusive event that was only experienced by the Jewish people. It’s interesting to note that this event which happened that was exclusive to the Jews is placed in a Parsha named after Yisro, a gentile- כהן מדין. Similarly, on Shavuos which is the Yom Tov celebrating Kabolas HaTorah, we read the story of Rus who at least originally was not Jewish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beshalach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Daily Song In this week’s Parsha, we read the Shiras HaYam. The Shiras HaYam was said as a reaction to the extraordinary miracle of Krias Yam Suf which the Jews just experienced. The Shira begins with אז ישיר משה ובני ישראל את השירה הזאת ויאמרו לאמר. The word לאמר is difficult to understand because it usually means that which is about to be said should be said over to someone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brachah of Al HaTzadikim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</guid>
      <description>This Shiur was given to the Beth Jacob community in Atlanta, GA 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bo</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yartzeit of Reb Avraham Weinfeld This week will be the Yahrzeit of the Rav’s father, Reb Avraham Weinfeld, on the 15th of Shevat. He was born in 1930, came to the United States in 1947 on the 15th of Shevat and passed away in 1987.
As the shul was davening outside, the Rav was thinking how spoiled people have become that standing outside in semi cold weather for an hour or two became such a challenge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Va&#39;era</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</guid>
      <description>5781 Hashem as the maker or breaker of nature וארא אל אברהם אל יצחק ואל יעקב באל שדי ושמי יקוק לא נודעתי להם The Parsha begins with Hashem telling Moshe that he appeared to Avraham, Yitzchak, and Yaakov as קל שקי but not with the Shem Havayeh. What is the difference between these two names of Hashem? The Ramban explains that the name שדי is from the word שודד-robber because when Hashem wants to work within the natural world, he takes away the power from the מזלות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inyanei Shovavim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</guid>
      <description>This Shmuz was said to the talmidim of Yeshivat HaKotel 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of the Rambam This past week, כ טבת, was the Yahrzeit of the Rambam. He was born in the year 1138 and died in 1204. It’s befitting for his Yahrzeit to fall out the week of Parshas Shemos (the year he died was on the Monday of Shemos like this year) as this is the first Parsha to mention Moshe Rabbeinu. The חסיד יעב&amp;quot;ץ, who lived during the time of the Spanish Inquisition, in his Sefer Ohr HaChaim in the beginning of Perek ט writes אשר כבר נתפרסם על הרמב&amp;quot;ם ממשה עד משה לא קם כמשה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayechi</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of the Bar Mitzvah of their son, Akiva Moshe.
Connection of Bar Mitzvah to Parsha This Shabbos is very appropriate for celebrating his Bar Mitzvah not only because it’s actually the week where he is becoming a Bar Mitzvah, but actually because Parshas Vayechi is apropos for a Bar Mitzvah as will be discussed.
(Once a Rebbe came to a village and a Jew came over to him and said Rebbe, in your on honor I’m going to make my son’s Bar Mitzvah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayigash</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</guid>
      <description>5781 Approaching One&amp;rsquo;s Self ויגש אליו יהודה ויאמר בי אדני ידבר נא עבדך דבר באזני אדני (מד,יח)
The Parshah begins with Yehuda bringing his case to Yosef. But what exactly was he saying new? He seems to be merely repeating the story that he and Yosef already knew and therefore what caused Yosef to now open up to the brothers?
One thing that Yehuda did add was that he made himself an ערב as the Pasuk says כי עבדך ערב את הנער מעם אבי אם לא אביאנו אליך (מד,לב).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miketz</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of Reb Eizel Charif This Shabbos, ד&#39; טבת, is the Yahrzeit of two great people. The first is Reb Yehoshua Isaac Shapiro, who was known as Reb Eizel Charif. He was born in 1801 in the small town of Glubki, near villna and he died in the year 1873. He was a tremendous gaon and very sharp/witty as his name indicates. He was also known for his sharp humor and until today many of his witticism are still known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeshev</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of the Raavad This Shabbos כ&amp;quot;ו כסלו is the Yahrzeit of the ראב&amp;quot;ד. The Raavad wrote other works but he is most known for his השגות on the Rambam.
The Raavad was Reb Avraham ben Dovid. He is known as the third Raavad. In in Hilchos Lulav (8:5) regarding the Halacha of נקטם by the הדסים writes the following: כבר הופיע רוח הקודש בבית מדרשנו מכמה שנים. Similarly in Hilchos Beis Habchira (6:14) he writes כך נגלה לי מסוד ה&#39; ליראיו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayishlach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Meaning of Dots ויפל על צוארו וישקהו ויבכו (לג,ד)
The Rav said the following vort from his father.
Rashi explains why there are נקודות on the word וישקהו. The first opinion is שלא נשקו בכל לבו. The second opinion of רשב&amp;quot;י is הלכה היא בידוע שעשו שונא ליעקב, אלא שנכמרו רחמיו באותה שעה ונשקו בכל לבו. The first explanation is according to the general rule that the נקודות are coming to minimize the meaning of the word that they are on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeitze</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</guid>
      <description>5781 You are where your mind is The Pasuk in the end of the Parshah says ויעקב הלך לדרכו ויפגעו בו מלאכי אלוקים. Rashi, quoting the Tanchuma, writes מלאכים של ארץ ישראל באו לקראתו ללוותו לארץ. This would seem to indicate that the Malachim went outside of Eretz Yisrael because Yaakov had not yet entered into Eretz Yisrael and the Malachim were already coming to greet him to escort him into Eretz Yisrael.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toldos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</guid>
      <description>5781 Greatness of the צדיק בן צדיק The Parshah begins ואלה תולדת יצחק בן אברהם אברהם הוליד את יצחק. As far as the meaning of the word תולדות, there are two opinions in the Rishonim. The Ramban, Ibn Ezra, and Sforno in the beginning of Parshas Noach explain that תולדות mean the “life story of”, and in that context is of Noach and doesn’t necessarily mean children. They support this because the Pasuk in Noach opens up with אלה תולדות נח and doesn’t speak about his children rather it continues נח איש צדיק תמים היה וכו&#39; and only in the next Pasuk does it then list his children.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chayei Sara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayera</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</guid>
      <description>5781 Haftorah The Haftorah discusses the interaction of Elisha with the wife of Ovadiah and then with the אשה השונמית. The Avudraham and the Levush explain the reason why this Haftorah was chosen for Parshas Vayera is because the second story is about אשה השונמית who had no children and was promised by Elisha that she would have a child. This is מענין הפרשה of Yitzchaks birth which says כעת חיה ולשרה בן and Rashi there explains this is the same expression Elisha uses when promising the אשה השונמית a child.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lech Lecha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</guid>
      <description>5781 Leave Everything Known and Familiar The Parshah begins with Hashem telling Avraham Avinu לך לך מארצך וממולדתך ומבית אביך. Although there are some who are of the opinion that the first נסיון Avraham encountered was the כבשן האש in אור כשדים which is not recorded in the Torah, the אבות דרב נתן and the Rambam in Peirush Hamishnayos אבות פרק חמישי are of the opinion that this command from Hashem was the first of the ten נסיונות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</guid>
      <description>5780 Celebration of Birth The Kiddush this week was sponsored by the Rossman family in honor of the birth of their daughter.
In Yiddish a למך is a לא יצלח so what did למך, the father of נח, do to have such a name? The Pasuk says the reason why his father named him Noach was because זה ינחמנו ממעשנו ומעצבון ידינו מן האדמה. A person that relies on his children to make a change and a difference in the world and doesn’t take the responsibility upon himself is a real למך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bereishis</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</guid>
      <description>5781 Shabbos Breishis This Shabbos is referred to as Shabbos Breishis, as opposed to other Shabbosos that we call it Shabbos Parshas Noach and the like. The Gemara in Baba Basra 121a actually refers to every Shabbos as “Shabbos Breishis” in the context that Shabbos does not require Kiddush Beis Din as opposed to the holidays of the year. However, the Minhag Yisrael is to refer to this Shabbos in particular as Shabbos Breishis which would seem to imply that that with this Shabbos we are beginning something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemini Atzeret 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sheminiatzeret_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sheminiatzeret_5780/</guid>
      <description>Shemini Atzeret as a Tikkun for Chet Mechirat Yosef</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haazinu 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu_5781/</guid>
      <description>This week we read the Shirah of Haazinu. Rashi along with others learn that the obligation in the Pasuk ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת is referring to Shiras Haazinu. But the Gemara in Sanhedrin 21b learns from that Pasuk the obligation of כתיבה ספר תורה which would seem to mean that השירה הזאת in the Pasuk is referring to כל התורה כולה. The Rambam manages to explain both that really the Shirah in the Pasuk refers to Haazinu, it’s just that one can’t write פרשיות פרשיות and therefore one is required to write the whole Torah so ממילא we see that there is a Mitzvah to write the whole Torah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shabbos Shuva 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva_5781/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Hashana</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
Sicha on Rosh Hashana 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim Vayelech 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Shabbos before Rosh Hashana is technically Shabbos Mevorchim however for Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, we are not mevarech the Chodesh. The Magen Avrohom says because it says בכסה ליום חגינו and therefore it is to be hidden. The Levush writes the reason is כדי לערבב את השטן. Perhaps another reason is as follows. The Gemara in Megilah 31b explains reason we have the Klalos of Devarim before Rosh Hashanah is כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה and the same is with Brachos as the Gemara says תחל שנה וברכותיה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Savo 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with the Mitzvah of Bikurim. Last week’s Parshah concludes with remembering Amalek. There is a Machlokes in Yevamos 4a as to whether or not we are דורש סמוכין. But even according to the one who holds we don’t דרשין סמוכין, he agrees that in Mishneh Torah, we are דורש סמוכין. This being the case, what is the connection between the Mitzvah of Bikurim and the Mitzvah of remembering of Amalek?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yemei Elul 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul_5780/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Chodesh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש. How can we understand this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eikev 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5780/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Parsha Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re&#39;eh 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5780/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Parsha Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bein HaMitzarim 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 24 Jul 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim_5780/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matos Masei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei_5780/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinchas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Jul 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</guid>
      <description>5779 קנאות People say that sometimes חקת and בלק are together and sometimes they are separate, as are מטות and, מסעי but פנחס is always by itself because the קנאי is always by himself.
קנאות is a word that is one of the most misused terms in Jewish life. Because if you look in the Mishna in סנהדרין צא ע&amp;quot;א you see that there are only four things that we say קנאין are פוגעין בו and the הלכה is אין מורין לו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balak</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</guid>
      <description>5780 Chessed Hashem to Connect We begin davening with the Pasuk מה טבו אהלך יעקב משכנתיך ישראל. This Pasuk appears in the Nevuah of Bilaam. However the Maharshal in Tshuvah 64 says not to say this Pasuk because he feels uncomfortable being that it was said by a Rasha such as Bilaam. But according to the understanding that the Pasuk is referring to בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות (סנהדרין קה) (which is why we say it when we walk into shul), it’s a powerful thing that even a Rasha like Bilaam recognized this attribute of Klal Yisrael and therefore all the more so of a reason that it should be included in our davening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chukas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</guid>
      <description>5779 Haftorah This week’s Haftorah discusses יפתח who went to war with בני עמון. The Gemara in ראש השנה דף כה ע&amp;quot;ב says יפתח בדורו כשמואל בדורו. The simple understanding of this Gemara is that in spite of the fact that יפתח was not a prophet and was just a warrior (ילקוט שמעוני ספר שופטים סז goes as far as to say he was not even a בן תורה), nonetheless for his generation he was as good as Shmuel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shavuos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</guid>
      <description>5780 There is a מנהג in כלל ישראל to put non-bearing fruit trees in shuls on שבועות because on עצרת the judgement for the upcoming year’s fruit tree is decided (מג&amp;quot;א או&amp;quot;ח ס&#39; תצד ס&amp;quot;ק ה). There are two questions that can be asked. Firstly, if we are judged in regard to fruit bearing trees, why do we put non fruit bearing trees in shul? Secondly, why is it that on ט&amp;quot;ו בשבת which is ראש השנה לאלנות do we celebrate by eating fruit and not with trees, an on שבועות which we are judged for the upcoming year’s fruit do we celebrate by putting trees in shuls, it should be the opposite?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tetzaveh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</guid>
      <description>5780 Zachor Confidence To Bounce Back The Mitzvah of זכירת עמלק is not just to incite the שנאה towards the people of Amalek but towards the evil aspect that which they represent, as the Maggid from Koznitz says that every Jew needs to eradicate the Amalek, that which it embodies and personifies, from within. There have been many enemies of the Jews in our history but we are only commanded to remember that which Amalek in order to not lose the שנאה over generations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sukkos 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos_5780/</guid>
      <description>The two main mitzvos throughout the Yom Tov of Sukkos are the ארבעה מינים and the סוכה. In the Torah, the Mitzvah of ארבעה מינים is told to us first and a few Psukim later we are commanded to sit in the Sukkah. However, when it comes to מסכת סוכה, the opposite is the case as the first two chapters deal with the Sukkah and only from the third chapter and on does it deal with the ארבעה מינים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabboscholhamoedsukkos_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabboscholhamoedsukkos_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Brachos for the Haftorah on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos are different than on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Pesach. On Shabbos Chol Hamoed Pesach, there is no mention of Pesach in Brachah על התורה nor does it end with מקדש השבת וישראל והזמנים. However, on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos, there is mention of חג הסוכות and it ends with מקדש השבת וישראל והזמנים. How could this be understood? A possible explanation could be as follows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayelech 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech_5780/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Kiddush was sponsored in honor of the Preidah for R’ Yackov Shwartzbaum. The Rav explained that it’s a סעודת מרעים, where friends get together. The Sefer HaChaim, written by Reb Chaim MVridburg (Brother of the Maharal) in the section titled ספר פרנסה וכלכלה, he writes that a סעודת מרעים, a seudah where people get together in friendship shouldn’t be a small thing in one’s eyes. Because it’s not for nothing that Chazal said that people shouldn’t break for Tefilah when they are involved in such a seudah because such a seudah is a big deal and is somewhat an expression of Tefilah, that which people nourish the אהבה between themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavim_5779/</guid>
      <description>The Gemara in מגילה דף לא ע&amp;quot;ב says that Ezra established that we should read the קללות in Vayikra before Shavuos and the קללות of Devarim before Rosh Hashanah כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה. It’s not merely because we finish the torah once a year that the קללות fall out near Rosh Hashanah rather its part of the Takana of Ezra, and even בני מערבא who competed the Torah in three years would read the קללות around Rosh Hashanah being it’s relevant for the time period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Seitzei 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of their sons Aufruf.
 The words כי יקח איש אשה appear three times in this week’s Parshah in the following Psukim. כי יקח איש אשה ובא אליה ושנאה (כב,יג) כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר וכתב לה ספר כריתת ונתן בידה ושלחה מביתו (כד,א) כי יקח איש אשה חדשה לא יצא בצבא ולא יעבר עליו לכל דבר נקי יהיה לביתו שנה אחת ושמח את אשתו אשר לקח (כד,ה) In fact, the source for כסף קדושין is learned out from the גזירה שוה of קיחה קיחה משדה עפרון and one of them is in the Parshah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoftim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim_5779/</guid>
      <description>The end of the Parshah deals with the עגלה ערופה. The Pasuk says ויצאו זקניך ושפטיך. Rashi says the זקניך are the סנהדרין גדולה. Every time a dead body was found, the entire Sanhedrin would have to get up from Jerusalem and travel to wherever the body was found. The question is who the beheaded heifer is coming to represent. One could have thought that it represents the murderer as the Pasuk says in the end of Parshas Masei ולארץ לא יכפר לדם אשר שפך בה כי אם בדם שפכו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re&#39;eh 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eikev 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5779/</guid>
      <description>The Rebbe Reb Bunim M’Pshichsa would learn Sefer Devarim every day of the year as a mussar sefer because what better mussar sefer could there be than to learn from the mussar of Moshe Rabbeinu. In the beginning of the Parshah, we find two references to יציאת מצרים. They are both two ways of living life and it’s the constant balance that must be kept throughout a person’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devarim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Chazon. The רמ&amp;quot;א סימן תקנא paskens that one should not wear בגדי שבת on Shabbos Chazon. The Mishnah Berura writes that in Vilna, they hold like the Gra and therefore they wear Shabbos clothing. However he is hesitant, and says that at least one garment should not be from בגדי שבת. But today everybody wears Shabbos clothing without a question. How could this be explained? The Rav suggested based on the מהרי&amp;quot;ל that says the reason we don’t wear Shabbos clothing on Shabbos Chazon even though there is a potential issue of אבילות בפרהסיא is because an onlooker who sees someone not wearing Shabbos clothing might assume that he doesn’t have any Shabbos clothing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masei 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/masei_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/masei_5779/</guid>
      <description>We say in the ברכות מעין שלש the words ונאכל מפריה ונשבע מטובה ונברך עליה בקדשה ובטהרה. The Poskim (See טור סימן רח) want to remove the words ונאכל מפריה ונשבע מטובה because of the Gemara in Sotah 14a. The Gemara there says as follows: דרש רבי שמלאי מפני מה נתאוה משה רבינו ליכנס לא&amp;quot;י וכי לאכול מפריה הוא צריך או לשבוע מטובה הוא צריך אלא כך אמר משה הרבה מצות נצטוו ישראל ואין מתקיימין אלא בא&amp;quot;י אכנס אני לארץ כדי שיתקיימו כולן על ידי The Gemara seems to indicate that it would be wrong if Moshe’s desire to enter EY was in order to eat the fruits and therefore gives another suggestion as to why Moshe desired to enter the land.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matos 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Parshah begins with the Parshah of Nedarim. Why is it mentioned specifically here, after the episode with Bilaam and Pinchas and between the story with the בנות מדין and the war against מדין? Rashi in Parshas Balak quotes the Chazal that tells us that Bilaam was given to theאומות העולם as a Navi כדי שלא יהא פתחון פה לאומות לומר אלו היו לנו נביאים חזרנו למוטב (כב,ה). The emphasis is on the פה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lashon Hara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</guid>
      <description>Who Wants Life? 5776</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Savo 5772</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5772/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Sep 2012 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5772/</guid>
      <description>Gratitude and Thankfulness</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Seitzei 5772</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5772/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Aug 2012 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5772/</guid>
      <description>Human Dignity</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
