<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rav Weinfeld</title>
    <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rav Weinfeld</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ravweinfeld.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Vayechi</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of the Bar Mitzvah of their son, Akiva Moshe.
Connection of Bar Mitzvah to Parsha This Shabbos is very appropriate for celebrating his Bar Mitzvah not only because it’s actually the week where he is becoming a Bar Mitzvah, but actually because Parshas Vayechi is apropos for a Bar Mitzvah as will be discussed.
(Once a Rebbe came to a village and a Jew came over to him and said Rebbe, in your on honor I’m going to make my son’s Bar Mitzvah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayigash</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</guid>
      <description>5781 Approaching One&amp;rsquo;s Self ויגש אליו יהודה ויאמר בי אדני ידבר נא עבדך דבר באזני אדני (מד,יח)
The Parshah begins with Yehuda bringing his case to Yosef. But what exactly was he saying new? He seems to be merely repeating the story that he and Yosef already knew and therefore what caused Yosef to now open up to the brothers?
One thing that Yehuda did add was that he made himself an ערב as the Pasuk says כי עבדך ערב את הנער מעם אבי אם לא אביאנו אליך (מד,לב).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chanukah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chanukah/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chanukah/</guid>
      <description>Videos Chanukah 5782 
Chanukah 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miketz</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of Reb Eizel Charif This Shabbos, ד&#39; טבת, is the Yahrzeit of two great people. The first is Reb Yehoshua Isaac Shapiro, who was known as Reb Eizel Charif. He was born in 1801 in the small town of Glubki, near villna and he died in the year 1873. He was a tremendous gaon and very sharp/witty as his name indicates. He was also known for his sharp humor and until today many of his witticism are still known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeshev</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of the Raavad This Shabbos כ&amp;quot;ו כסלו is the Yahrzeit of the ראב&amp;quot;ד. The Raavad wrote other works but he is most known for his השגות on the Rambam.
The Raavad was Reb Avraham ben Dovid. He is known as the third Raavad. In in Hilchos Lulav (8:5) regarding the Halacha of נקטם by the הדסים writes the following: כבר הופיע רוח הקודש בבית מדרשנו מכמה שנים. Similarly in Hilchos Beis Habchira (6:14) he writes כך נגלה לי מסוד ה&#39; ליראיו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayishlach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</guid>
      <description>5782 Jewish Identity Parshas Vayishlach begins with the confrontation between Yaakov and Eisav. This confrontation is really the story of the Jewish people throughout history. The Ramban writes that Reb Yehuda HaNasi would learn Parshas Vayishlach before he dealt with the Romans.
Yaakov wrestles with the שרו של עשו and he says to him הגידה נא שמך and the Malach responds למה זה תשאל לשמי. This could be understood that throughout history, the Jewish people are always trying to fit into a specific society and culture and to blend in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeitze</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</guid>
      <description>5782 Impact of the Departure ויצא יעקב מבאר שבע וילך חרנה
Regarding why the Torah says ויצא and וילך, Rashi writes לא היה צריך לכתוב אלא וילך יעקב חרנה, ולמה הזכיר יציאתו, אלא מגיד שיציאת צדיק מן המקום עושה רושם, שבזמן שהצדיק בעיר הוא הודה הוא זיוה הוא הדרה, יצא משם פנה הודהה פנה זיוה פנה הדרה. It’s not clear what the תועלת is in telling us that יציאת צדיק מן המקום עושה רושם.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toldos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</guid>
      <description>5782 This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by Mikey Perl in honor of the birth of his daughter Shoshana.
ואלה תולדות This Shabbos is an appropriate Shabbos to celebrate a Kiddush being that the Parshah is about Toldos. There are two Parshiyos that begin with ואלה תולדות. One of them is called Toldos and the other is called Noach. If we don’t want to call two Parshiyos the same name, one would think it would be better to call a Parshah after Yitzchak instead of Noach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chayei Sara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</guid>
      <description>5782 Chosson Torah The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Eli Rudansky for חתן תורה. A חתן תורה needs to remember that which Chazal say in Kiddushin 41aאמר רב יהודה אמר רב: אסור לאדם שיקדש את האשה עד שיראנה שמא יראה בה דבר מגונה ותתגנה עליו. It must be that if he became a חתן תורה, then he was already יראנה and he knows that it appeals to him. So we want to give a Brachah to the חתן תורה that he should be zocheh that Torah should always be pleasant to him והערב נא ה&#39; אלקינו את דברי תורתך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayera</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</guid>
      <description>5781 Haftorah The Haftorah discusses the interaction of Elisha with the wife of Ovadiah and then with the אשה השונמית. The Avudraham and the Levush explain the reason why this Haftorah was chosen for Parshas Vayera is because the second story is about אשה השונמית who had no children and was promised by Elisha that she would have a child. This is מענין הפרשה of Yitzchaks birth which says כעת חיה ולשרה בן and Rashi there explains this is the same expression Elisha uses when promising the אשה השונמית a child.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lech Lecha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</guid>
      <description>5781 Leave Everything Known and Familiar The Parshah begins with Hashem telling Avraham Avinu לך לך מארצך וממולדתך ומבית אביך. Although there are some who are of the opinion that the first נסיון Avraham encountered was the כבשן האש in אור כשדים which is not recorded in the Torah, the אבות דרב נתן and the Rambam in Peirush Hamishnayos אבות פרק חמישי are of the opinion that this command from Hashem was the first of the ten נסיונות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</guid>
      <description>5780 Celebration of Birth The Kiddush this week was sponsored by the Rossman family in honor of the birth of their daughter.
In Yiddish a למך is a לא יצלח so what did למך, the father of נח, do to have such a name? The Pasuk says the reason why his father named him Noach was because זה ינחמנו ממעשנו ומעצבון ידינו מן האדמה. A person that relies on his children to make a change and a difference in the world and doesn’t take the responsibility upon himself is a real למך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bereishis</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</guid>
      <description>5781 Shabbos Breishis This Shabbos is referred to as Shabbos Breishis, as opposed to other Shabbosos that we call it Shabbos Parshas Noach and the like. The Gemara in Baba Basra 121a actually refers to every Shabbos as “Shabbos Breishis” in the context that Shabbos does not require Kiddush Beis Din as opposed to the holidays of the year. However, the Minhag Yisrael is to refer to this Shabbos in particular as Shabbos Breishis which would seem to imply that that with this Shabbos we are beginning something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haazinu</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu/</guid>
      <description>5781 Luchos Shniyos This week we read the Shirah of Haazinu. Rashi along with others learn that the obligation in the Pasuk ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת is referring to Shiras Haazinu. But the Gemara in Sanhedrin 21b learns from that Pasuk the obligation of כתיבה ספר תורה which would seem to mean that השירה הזאת in the Pasuk is referring to כל התורה כולה. The Rambam manages to explain both that really the Shirah in the Pasuk refers to Haazinu, it’s just that one can’t write פרשיות פרשיות and therefore one is required to write the whole Torah so ממילא we see that there is a Mitzvah to write the whole Torah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim Vayelech</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech/</guid>
      <description>Vayelech - 5782 Have Mercy and Be Happy with us We say in the davening on Rosh Hashanah ותשמח במעשיך חמול על מעשיך that Hashem should have compassion and mercy on us and that Hashem should be happy with us. These two statements seem to be a contradiction. We begin saying that we are unworthy when we ask חמול על מעשיך but then we immediately say ותשמח במעשיך to be happy with us, which sounds like we are claiming to be worthy and good people?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yom Kippur</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5782 
Thursday Night Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Hashana</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5782 
Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
Sicha on Rosh Hashana 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yemei Elul</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul/</guid>
      <description>Videos Motsei Shabbos Slichos 5781 
Thursday Night Shiur 5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Savo</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Aryeh Leib Reich for the upcoming Yahrzeit of his father.
Death Gives Meaning The Jewish people tend to give more time to commemorating Yahrzeits than to celebrating births. The reason could be because death is really what qualifies living as the Gemara Brachos 5a says יצר הרע מתגבר עליו יזכיר לו יום המיתה. Remembering that life has an end encourages us us to focus on what’s important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Seitzei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei/</guid>
      <description>5779 Aufruf This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of their sons Aufruf.
The words כי יקח איש אשה appear three times in this week’s Parshah in the following Psukim. כי יקח איש אשה ובא אליה ושנאה (כב,יג)
כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר וכתב לה ספר כריתת ונתן בידה ושלחה מביתו (כד,א)
כי יקח איש אשה חדשה לא יצא בצבא ולא יעבר עליו לכל דבר נקי יהיה לביתו שנה אחת ושמח את אשתו אשר לקח (כד,ה)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoftim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Kiddush Sponsorship The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Naftali Kasorla in honor of the birth of his daughter, Chava Sheindel.
Adam Harishon named his wife Chava as the Pasuk says ויקרא האדם שם אשתו חוה כי הוא היתה אם כל חי. Rashi says that חוה is from the לשון of חיה. The Baal HaTurim says על שם שמחוה וזהו שאמרו (קידושין מט ב) יו&amp;quot;ד קבין שיחה ירדו לעולם, תשעה נטלו נשים ואחת כל העולם that it’s from a לשון of talking, like it says ולילה ללילה יחוה דעת.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re&#39;eh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh/</guid>
      <description>5781 Kiddush Sponsorship The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Matisyahu Ginsberger in honor of the birth of a baby boy. Although usually a boy has the bris and a baby girl has a Kiddush, the Baal Simchah felt, due to a variety factors, that the birth of this child warranted an additional Kiddush. Regarding this feeling that was felt by the Baal Simchah, the Rav said over the following Radak.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eikev</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev/</guid>
      <description>5779 Right Mindset The Rebbe Reb Bunim M’Pshichsa would learn Sefer Devarim every day of the year as a mussar sefer because what better mussar sefer could there be than to learn from the mussar of Moshe Rabbeinu. In the beginning of the Parshah, we find two references to יציאת מצרים. They are both two ways of living life and it’s the constant balance that must be kept throughout a person’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaeschanan</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaeschanan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaeschanan/</guid>
      <description>5781 Consolation in the Galus The three Shabbasos before Tisha BaAv are called the תלתא דפורענותא because during these Shabosos, we read Haftorahs that talk about the Churban instead of reading a Haftorah which is מענין הפרשה. The seven weeks after Tisha BaAv, beginning with this Shabbos, are known as the שב דנחמתא since the Haftorah of each of these weeks discuss consolation. The תלתא דפורענותא are understandable as we are still in Galus and are still waiting for the building of the Beis Hamikdash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devarim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Blind Spot This Shabbos, ח אב, is the Yahrzeit of the Alter from Kelm. The Rav mentioned that in Kelm, on a Yahrzeit, a Yasom didn’t daven at the Amud. They would say the reason is because the Amud is not a Yasom. (This was prompted by someone in the Shul having Yahrzeit and not davening for the Amud.)
In the Sefer חכמה ומוסר (Volume 2, Siman 71, titled מכל מלמדי השכלתי), the Alter from Kelm writes something that is connected to the beginning of Devarim (1:9-14).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bein HaMitzarim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
Thursday Night Shiur 5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matos Masei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei/</guid>
      <description>Matos 5779 Importance of Speech This week’s Parshah begins with the Parshah of Nedarim. Why is it mentioned specifically here, after the episode with Bilaam and Pinchas and between the story with the בנות מדין and the war against מדין?
Rashi in Parshas Balak quotes the Chazal that tells us that Bilaam was given to theאומות העולם as a Navi כדי שלא יהא פתחון פה לאומות לומר אלו היו לנו נביאים חזרנו למוטב (כב,ה).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinchas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit, the Churban, and Moadim The Kiddush was sponsored by Sender Galbut לעלוי נשמת his father, Reb Boruch Tzvi Ben Reuven Nosson Z”L. Dr. Galbut had visited the shul twice when he was already terminally ill and nevertheless he had a captivating smile and radiated Simchah. He was Zocheh that his Yahrzeit be during the ימי המצרים which are anyways days of mourning so he didn’t add another day of sadness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balak</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</guid>
      <description>5780 Chessed Hashem to Connect We begin davening with the Pasuk מה טבו אהלך יעקב משכנתיך ישראל. This Pasuk appears in the Nevuah of Bilaam. However the Maharshal in Tshuvah 64 says not to say this Pasuk because he feels uncomfortable being that it was said by a Rasha such as Bilaam. But according to the understanding that the Pasuk is referring to בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות (סנהדרין קה) (which is why we say it when we walk into shul), it’s a powerful thing that even a Rasha like Bilaam recognized this attribute of Klal Yisrael and therefore all the more so of a reason that it should be included in our davening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chukas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</guid>
      <description>5779 Haftorah This week’s Haftorah discusses יפתח who went to war with בני עמון. The Gemara in ראש השנה דף כה ע&amp;quot;ב says יפתח בדורו כשמואל בדורו. The simple understanding of this Gemara is that in spite of the fact that יפתח was not a prophet and was just a warrior (ילקוט שמעוני ספר שופטים סז goes as far as to say he was not even a בן תורה), nonetheless for his generation he was as good as Shmuel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Korach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Motivation for Machlokes The Parsha begins ויקח קרח בן יצהר בן קהת בן לוי ודתן ואבירם בני אליאב ואון בן פלת בני ראובן. This coalition was made up of a group of individuals who were all seeking different things, some the נשיאות and some the כהונה. Although און בן פלת didn’t really have a claim, it could be that he was the man behind the ideological טענה of כל העדה כלם קדשים ובתוכם יקוק ומדוע תתנשאו על קהל ה&#39;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shelach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Wise and Righteous The Parsha begins שלח לך אנשים. Rashi on the words כלם אנשים says כל אנשים שבמקרא לשון חשיבות ואותה שעה כשרים היו meaning they were Tzadikim. The Targum Yonason Ben Uziel says on the word אנשים that they were חריפין-sharp/astute people. Lastly, the Ibn Ezra says on the word אנשים that they were גבורים. So it would appear that everyone agrees that אנשים is a לשון of חשובים but there are three ways in explaining in what their חשיבות was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaloscha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</guid>
      <description>5781 Opportunity When Out of Place The Parsha begins with Ahron being commanded בהעלתך את הנרת. Rashi points out that this Parshas is out of place by asking למה נסמכה פרשת המנורה לפרשת הנשיאים because if these events occurred chronologically, then there would be no need for such a question. Therefore, the fact that Rashi asks למה נסמכה indicates that this event is not in the chronological order of event as we see in the Gemara in Gittin on 60b that the Parshah of the Menorah was one of the eight Parshiyos given on Rosh Chodesh Nissan before the Nesiim began to bring their Korbanos and it wasn’t said now, after the Nesiim concluded bringing their Korbanos, which was on the twelfth day of Nissan.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naso</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</guid>
      <description>5781 Importance of personal connection The second half of the Parsha discusses the Korbanos that were brought by the Nesiim by the Chanukas Hamishkan. Although the Nesiim brought identical Korbanos, the Torah spells out the Korbanos that each Nasi brought. It would seem to make more sense for the Torah to write it once and then say that this is what each Nasi brought. What is the significance and message being taught that the Korbanos of each Nasi is written out even though it is seemingly repetitious as they are all identical?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bamidbar</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Great Scribe and Counter The Kiddush was sponsored by the Schreiber family in honor of the birth of a baby girl.
The word Schreiber is very much connected to Parshas Bamidbar because Shcreiber means “writer”. The Gemara in Sotah 13b refers to Moshe Rabbeinu as the ספרא רבה דישראל, which simply means the great scribe of Yisrael. Why is Moshe Rabbeinu called the great scribe of Yisrael?
The Maharsha there is bothered why Moshe is called the ספרא רבה דישראל, specifically the great scribe of the Jews if the writing of the Torah was on behalf of Hashem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behar Bechukosai</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beharbechukosai/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beharbechukosai/</guid>
      <description>5781 Meron Tragedy In connection with the terrible tragedy that happened in Meron where so many young people, each one special in his own way, were plucked from us in such a quick and cruel way. People have been searching for meaning and therefore we should start with the simple and basic meaning of all this.
The Rav began with a story he heard from his Rebbe Reb Berel Soloveitchik. Reb Chaim Brisker had three sons and the least known was Reb Yisrael Gershon who was a bit eccentric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emor</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</guid>
      <description>5781 כל הגדול מחבירו יצרו גדול הימנו The Parsha begins with the many mitzvos that apply only to Kohanim. The Gemara in Yevamos 5a says שאני כהנים הואיל וריבה בהן הכתוב מצות יתירות that Kohanim are unique in the sense that they have many more Mitzvos that only apply to them.
One could ask why is it that the Kohanim specifically are the people who have more Mitzvos than other Jews.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lag Baomer</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acharei Kedoshim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/achareikedoshim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/achareikedoshim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Mourning Loss in the Link Parshas Acharei begins immediately following the death of Aarons two sons, נדב ואביהו as the Pasuk says וידבר ה&#39; אל משה אחרי מות שני בני אהרן. The באר היטב in אורח חיים סימן תרכ&amp;quot;א brings in the name of the Zohar and the Arizal that when the Psukim discussing the death of Aarons sons is being read on Yom Kippur, יש להצטער על מיתתן ולהוריד עליהם דמעות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tazria Metzorah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazriametzorah/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazriametzorah/</guid>
      <description>5781 The טומאה of a יולדת Parshas Tazria begins with טומאת יולדת. Regarding her טומאה state, the Pasuk says בכל קדש לא תגע and Rashi writes לרבות את התרומה, לפי שזו טבולת יום ארוך, שטבלה לסוף שבעה ואין שמשה מעריב לטהרה עד שקיעת החמה של יום ארבעים, שלמחר תביא את כפרת טהרתה. A יולדת has a status of a טבול יום ארוך because she remains a טבול יום either for 33 days or 66 days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemini</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pesach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</guid>
      <description>Videos Krias Yam Suf 5781 
Inyanei Haggadah 
The Order on the Seder Night 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayikra</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781 
Language of Affection 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayakhel Pekudei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhelpekudei/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhelpekudei/</guid>
      <description>5781 Pleasantness Throughout The Week וירא משה את כל המלאכה והנה עשו אתה כאשר צוה יקוק כן עשו ויברך אתם משה (לט,מג)
Rashi explains אמר להם יהי רצון שתשרה שכינה במעשה ידיכם, (תהלים צ יז) ויהי נועם ה&#39; אלהינו עלינו ומעשה ידינו וגו. Moshe Rabbeinu gave a Brachah that the Shechina should reside in the Mishkan. The Pasuk says that the Mishkan was erected on Rosh Chodesh Nissan and the Gemara in Shabbos 87b says that day was the first day of the week-ראשון למעשה בראשית.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Sisa</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Mar 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</guid>
      <description>5780 Hold On This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by Reb Yisrael Neuberger in honor of his new book “Hold On”. (On the cover, there is a rope so the Rav digressed on the idea of a חבל.)
The word חבל not only means a rope but at times is used to describe a גרל as the Pasuk says in Haazinu כי חלק יקוק עמו יעקב חבל נחלתו( לב,ט). Now if every creation and creature in this world has a specific purpose as it says לא ברא הקב&amp;quot;ה דבר אחד לבטלה (במ&amp;quot;ר יח,יח, זהר א כג), then all the more so, the human being which is created בצלם אלוקים for sure has a purpose and a mission that only he can fulfil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</guid>
      <description>5780 Haman thought that Adar was a month of bad luck for the Jews because of the death of Moshe and it was probably a painful and difficult day for the Jews being that they lost the greatest leader in history. But the Jews pulled it together and on that day they learned a very important lesson. They learned that as a people we must keep moving on and with the death comes a new beginning and opportunity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terumah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</guid>
      <description>5781 Shabbos Zachor The Kiddush was sponsored by Reb Shalom Huss in memory of his father. Once a person continues on to the next world, he is no longer able to do Mitzvos and reach higher levels, he is no longer a מהלך. However, the living are able to make a Brachah לעילוי נשמתו and it can affect the נשמה. The Gemara says about a son ברא כרעיה דאבוה that a son is like a leg of his father which can be understood to mean that one’s father can continue walking through the Mitzvos that his son performs in this world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mishpatim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Emphasis of Mishpatim The Parsha begins ואלה המשפטים אשר תשים לפניהם. Rashi says:
אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא למשה לא תעלה על דעתך לומר אשנה להם הפרק וההלכה ב&#39; או ג&#39; פעמים עד שתהא סדורה בפיהם כמשנתה, ואיני מטריח עצמי להבינם טעמי הדבר ופירושו, לכך נאמר אשר תשים לפניהם, כשלחן הערוך ומוכן לאכול לפני האדם.
Hashem told Moshe that he shouldn’t just teach Klal Yisrael the Torah a few times until they are well versed and not explain the טעמי המצות rather he should teach them with their טעמים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yisro</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</guid>
      <description>5781 A Torah For All In this week’s Parsha, the Jewish people received the Torah at Har Sinai. The revelation at Sinai was a very exclusive event that was only experienced by the Jewish people. It’s interesting to note that this event which happened that was exclusive to the Jews is placed in a Parsha named after Yisro, a gentile- כהן מדין. Similarly, on Shavuos which is the Yom Tov celebrating Kabolas HaTorah, we read the story of Rus who at least originally was not Jewish.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beshalach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Daily Song In this week’s Parsha, we read the Shiras HaYam. The Shiras HaYam was said as a reaction to the extraordinary miracle of Krias Yam Suf which the Jews just experienced. The Shira begins with אז ישיר משה ובני ישראל את השירה הזאת ויאמרו לאמר. The word לאמר is difficult to understand because it usually means that which is about to be said should be said over to someone.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brachah of Al HaTzadikim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</guid>
      <description>This Shiur was given to the Beth Jacob community in Atlanta, GA 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bo</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 21 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yartzeit of Reb Avraham Weinfeld This week will be the Yahrzeit of the Rav’s father, Reb Avraham Weinfeld, on the 15th of Shevat. He was born in 1930, came to the United States in 1947 on the 15th of Shevat and passed away in 1987.
As the shul was davening outside, the Rav was thinking how spoiled people have become that standing outside in semi cold weather for an hour or two became such a challenge.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Va&#39;era</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</guid>
      <description>5781 Hashem as the maker or breaker of nature וארא אל אברהם אל יצחק ואל יעקב באל שדי ושמי יקוק לא נודעתי להם The Parsha begins with Hashem telling Moshe that he appeared to Avraham, Yitzchak, and Yaakov as קל שקי but not with the Shem Havayeh. What is the difference between these two names of Hashem? The Ramban explains that the name שדי is from the word שודד-robber because when Hashem wants to work within the natural world, he takes away the power from the מזלות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inyanei Shovavim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</guid>
      <description>This Shmuz was said to the talmidim of Yeshivat HaKotel 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of the Rambam This past week, כ טבת, was the Yahrzeit of the Rambam. He was born in the year 1138 and died in 1204. It’s befitting for his Yahrzeit to fall out the week of Parshas Shemos (the year he died was on the Monday of Shemos like this year) as this is the first Parsha to mention Moshe Rabbeinu. The חסיד יעב&amp;quot;ץ, who lived during the time of the Spanish Inquisition, in his Sefer Ohr HaChaim in the beginning of Perek ט writes אשר כבר נתפרסם על הרמב&amp;quot;ם ממשה עד משה לא קם כמשה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vzos HaBrachah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vzoshabrachah/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vzoshabrachah/</guid>
      <description>Simultaneously מורשה and מאורסה In the beginning of Vzos Brachah, the Pasuk says תורה צוה לנו משה מורשה קהלת יעקב. Chazal are דורש this Pasuk saying אל תקרי מורשה אלא מאורסה.
But how could it be that Chazal are switching the entire meaning of the Pasuk because מורשה and מאורסה are seemingly diametrically opposed. A מורשה is ירושה and קנינים apply to ירושה because the מעשה קנין is just bringing something that already exists into my ownership, like it says in Behar כי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך וכו&#39; that the ממכר existed before it was mine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Chodesh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש. How can we understand this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shavuos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</guid>
      <description>5780 There is a מנהג in כלל ישראל to put non-bearing fruit trees in shuls on שבועות because on עצרת the judgement for the upcoming year’s fruit tree is decided (מג&amp;quot;א או&amp;quot;ח ס&#39; תצד ס&amp;quot;ק ה). There are two questions that can be asked. Firstly, if we are judged in regard to fruit bearing trees, why do we put non fruit bearing trees in shul? Secondly, why is it that on ט&amp;quot;ו בשבת which is ראש השנה לאלנות do we celebrate by eating fruit and not with trees, an on שבועות which we are judged for the upcoming year’s fruit do we celebrate by putting trees in shuls, it should be the opposite?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tetzaveh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</guid>
      <description>5780 Zachor Confidence To Bounce Back The Mitzvah of זכירת עמלק is not just to incite the שנאה towards the people of Amalek but towards the evil aspect that which they represent, as the Maggid from Koznitz says that every Jew needs to eradicate the Amalek, that which it embodies and personifies, from within. There have been many enemies of the Jews in our history but we are only commanded to remember that which Amalek in order to not lose the שנאה over generations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sukkos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos/</guid>
      <description>5780 The two main mitzvos throughout the Yom Tov of Sukkos are the ארבעה מינים and the סוכה. In the Torah, the Mitzvah of ארבעה מינים is told to us first and a few Psukim later we are commanded to sit in the Sukkah. However, when it comes to מסכת סוכה, the opposite is the case as the first two chapters deal with the Sukkah and only from the third chapter and on does it deal with the ארבעה מינים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayelech</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech/</guid>
      <description>5780 Seudah with Friends This week’s Kiddush was sponsored in honor of the Preidah for R’ Yackov Shwartzbaum. The Rav explained that it’s a סעודת מרעים, where friends get together. The Sefer HaChaim, written by Reb Chaim MVridburg (Brother of the Maharal) in the section titled ספר פרנסה וכלכלה, he writes that a סעודת מרעים, a seudah where people get together in friendship shouldn’t be a small thing in one’s eyes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lashon Hara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</guid>
      <description>Who Wants Life? 5776</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Search</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/search/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
