<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Rav Weinfeld</title>
    <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Rav Weinfeld</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 11:30:03 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ravweinfeld.com/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Shelach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Wise and Righteous The Parsha begins שלח לך אנשים. Rashi on the words כלם אנשים says כל אנשים שבמקרא לשון חשיבות ואותה שעה כשרים היו meaning they were Tzadikim. The Targum Yonason Ben Uziel says on the word אנשים that they were חריפין-sharp/astute people. Lastly, the Ibn Ezra says on the word אנשים that they were גבורים. So it would appear that everyone agrees that אנשים is a לשון of חשובים but there are three ways in explaining in what their חשיבות was.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaloscha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha/</guid>
      <description>5782 Teshuvah The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Yisrael (Roy) Neuberger in honor of his mother in laws Yahrzeit. She discovered the beauty of Yiddishkeit during the last years of her life through her children as Rashi says on the Pasuk in the end of Malachi 3:24 והשיב לב אבות על בנים ולב בנים על אבותם, Rashi says אבות ע&amp;quot;י בנים that children will bring their parents back at the end of days.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shavuos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</guid>
      <description>5780 There is a מנהג in כלל ישראל to put non-bearing fruit trees in shuls on שבועות because on עצרת the judgement for the upcoming year’s fruit tree is decided (מג&amp;quot;א או&amp;quot;ח ס&#39; תצד ס&amp;quot;ק ה). There are two questions that can be asked. Firstly, if we are judged in regard to fruit bearing trees, why do we put non fruit bearing trees in shul? Secondly, why is it that on ט&amp;quot;ו בשבת which is ראש השנה לאלנות do we celebrate by eating fruit and not with trees, an on שבועות which we are judged for the upcoming year’s fruit do we celebrate by putting trees in shuls, it should be the opposite?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naso</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso/</guid>
      <description>5781 Importance of personal connection The second half of the Parsha discusses the Korbanos that were brought by the Nesiim by the Chanukas Hamishkan. Although the Nesiim brought identical Korbanos, the Torah spells out the Korbanos that each Nasi brought. It would seem to make more sense for the Torah to write it once and then say that this is what each Nasi brought. What is the significance and message being taught that the Korbanos of each Nasi is written out even though it is seemingly repetitious as they are all identical?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bamidbar</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 24 May 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Great Scribe and Counter The Kiddush was sponsored by the Schreiber family in honor of the birth of a baby girl.
The word Schreiber is very much connected to Parshas Bamidbar because Shcreiber means “writer”. The Gemara in Sotah 13b refers to Moshe Rabbeinu as the ספרא רבה דישראל, which simply means the great scribe of Yisrael. Why is Moshe Rabbeinu called the great scribe of Yisrael?
The Maharsha there is bothered why Moshe is called the ספרא רבה דישראל, specifically the great scribe of the Jews if the writing of the Torah was on behalf of Hashem.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bechukosai</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bechukosai/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 May 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bechukosai/</guid>
      <description>5781 לחמכם בתנור אחד In the תוכחה, the Pasuk says ואפו עשר נשים לחמכם בתנור אחד (כו,כו). Rashi says the reason will be because מחוסר עצים-out of lack of wood. However the Rashbam says כי אשה אחת לא תוכל למלא את התנור פת meaning there will be a lack of food. How did Rashi know to explain the reason why ten women will bake in one oven is because of the lack of wood?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behar</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behar/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 May 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behar/</guid>
      <description>5782 Emphasis on the Details The Parshah begins וידבר ה&#39; אל משה בהר סיני לאמר. Rashi, quoting the Toras Kohanim, writes מה ענין שמיטה אצל הר סיני, והלא כל המצות נאמרו מסיני, אלא מה שמיטה נאמרו כללותיה ופרטותיה ודקדוקיה מסיני, אף כולן נאמרו כללותיהן ודקדוקיהן מסיני. Why is there an emphasis that not only were the כללות said at Sinai but also the דקדוקיהן and פרטות were given at Sinai?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emor</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/emor/</guid>
      <description>5782 Seeing Hashem in our Life and Success The Parshah begins with the איסור for כהנים to be מטמא למת. This needs to be explained because one would think that an encounter with the dead is inspiring and it teaches a person that life isn’t only about living and Oilam Hazeh butהעולם הזה דומה לפרוזדור בפני העולם הבא התקן עצמך בפרוזדור כדי שתכנס לטרקלין (אבות ד:טז) and that we aren’t here to say and that a person shouldn’t overly focus on this world.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Kedoshim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kedoshim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Apr 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kedoshim/</guid>
      <description>5782 Dovid HaMelech and the Moon The Haftorah of this week’s Shabbos is מחר חודש. Since tomorrow is Rosh Chodesh, so we read the Haftorah of מחר חודש. The Gemara in Megilah 31a says the following:
ראש חדש שחל להיות בשבת מפטירין והיה מדי חדש בחדשו. חל להיות באחד בשבת, מאתמול מפטירין ויאמר לו יהונתן מחר חדש
This Gemara is brought down in the Rambam Hilchos Tefilah 13:4 and in Shulchan Aruch Siman 425.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Acharei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/acharei/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 24 Apr 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/acharei/</guid>
      <description>5781 Mourning Loss in the Link Parshas Acharei begins immediately following the death of Aarons two sons, נדב ואביהו as the Pasuk says וידבר ה&#39; אל משה אחרי מות שני בני אהרן. The באר היטב in אורח חיים סימן תרכ&amp;quot;א brings in the name of the Zohar and the Arizal that when the Psukim discussing the death of Aarons sons is being read on Yom Kippur, יש להצטער על מיתתן ולהוריד עליהם דמעות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pesach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pesach/</guid>
      <description>Videos Shiras HaYam 5782 
Sippur Yetzias Mitzrayim 5782 
Krias Yam Suf 5781 
Inyanei Haggadah 5781 
The Order on the Seder Night 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Metzorah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/metzorah/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/metzorah/</guid>
      <description>5782 Shabbos HaGadol This Shabbos is called Shabbos HaGadol. The Shulchan Aruch dedicates an entire Siman to this and writes in Siman 430 שבת שלפני הפסח קורין אותו שבת הגדול מפני הנס שנעשה בו. What is the Halachic significance of קורין אותו שבת הגדול? Interestingly, the Chidah writes in his Sefer מחזיק ברכה ס&#39; תל that on a regular Shabbos, people greet each other with שבת שלום ומבורך but on Shabbos HaGadol, the מדקדקים greet each other with שבת הגדול שלום ומבורך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tazria</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazria/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 28 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tazria/</guid>
      <description>5782 Three Sifrei Torah This Shabbos we read from three Sifrei Torah. This only happens on the following three occurrences. Rosh Chodesh Teves that falls out on Shabbos Chanukah where we read the Parshah Hashavuah, the reading of Rosh Chodesh and the reading for Chanukah. Rosh Chodesh Adar falls out on Shabbos where we read Parshas Shekalim along with the Parsha Hashavua and Rosh Chodesh. Rosh Chodesh Nissan falls out on Shabbos where we read Parshas Hachodesh along with the Parshah Hashavua and Rosh Chodesh.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hesped on Reb Chaim Kanievsky Zatzal</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hesped/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hesped/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tzav</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tzav/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tzav/</guid>
      <description>5782 Emunah Peshutah Today is the 16th day of Adar. In the end of the Megilah, the Pasuk says קימו וקבלו היהודים עליהם ועל זרעם ועל כל הנלוים עליהם ולא יעבור להיות עשים את שני הימים האלה ככתבם וכזמנם בכל שנה ושנה. The Gemara in Megilah learns from the words לא יעבור that the latest day one can read the Megilah is on the 15th but not later.
The next Pasuk says והימים האלה נזכרים ונעשים בכל דור ודור משפחה ומשפחה מדינה ומדינה ועיר ועיר וימי הפורים האלה לא יעברו מתוך היהודים וזכרם לא יסוף מזרעם.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayikra</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayikra/</guid>
      <description>5782 Connection Between Vayikra and Zachor In a שנה מעוברת, which occurs seven times in nineteen years, we read Parshas Zachor together with Vayikra. In spite of the fact that the reading of Vayikra is based on the yearly cycle of פרשה השבוע and the reading of Parshas Zachor is מעיניא דיומא as the Chinuch writes in מצוה תרג that Zachor should be read the Shabbos before Purim because Haman was a descendent of Amalek, nevertheless we can find a connection between the two.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Mar 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</guid>
      <description>5781 פורים משולש First In Megilah Esther, the Pasuk says קימו וקבלו היהודים עליהם ועל זרעם ועל כל הנלוים עליהם (ט,כז). The Gra says on the words ועל זרעם that it’s referring to קטנים, that the Jews were מקבל on themselves and their children. But קטנים are פטור from all Mitzvos so how were they מקבל for their children. It would seem that this Mitzvah, קריאת מגילה, is an exception to the rule and the Mitzvah of Megilah was taken upon the קטנים as well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pekudei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pekudei/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Feb 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pekudei/</guid>
      <description>5782 Yahrzeit of the מהרי&amp;quot;ט אלגאזי This Shabbos, ב&#39; אדר שני, is the Yahrzeit of the מהרי&amp;quot;ט אלגאזי-Rabbi Yom Tov Algazi who lived in Yerushalayim, who was nifter in 1802. He authored a commentary on the הלכות הרמב&amp;quot;ן on בכורות and חלה. Reb Avraham Weinfeld came to the concentration camps when he was fourteen and he had already learned the מהרי&amp;quot;ט אלגאזי on בכורות. He said that it was such a popular לימוד that people would learn בכורות just in order to learn the מהרי&amp;quot;ט אלגאזי.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayakhel</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayakhel/</guid>
      <description>5782 Necessity of Togetherness and Readiness The Parshah begins ויקהל משה את כל עדת בני ישראל. Moshe Rabbeinu is congregating כל עדת בני ישראל to tell them the ציווי of בנין המשכן. The fact that the Torah emphasizes the ויקהל, in the context of the ציווי of בנין המשכן shows the importance of ויקהל- togetherness, for בנין המשכן.
Similarly, the Haftarah for Parshas Pekudei which discusses the Beis HaMikdash that Shlomo Hamelech built, writes אז יקהל שלמה את זקני ישראל וכו&#39; ויקהלו אל המלך שלמה כל איש ישראל וכו&#39;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Sisa</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Feb 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa/</guid>
      <description>5782 Qualifying Actions The Minhag to call up a Levi for the Aliyah which has the חטא העגל is brought down in the Magen Avraham Siman 428:8 . The reason is as explained in the Magen Avraham in the end of Siman 138 in the name of Sefer Chasidim 768 that we don&amp;rsquo;t call up someone, who is suspected of doing a particular aveira, for the Psukim that mention that aveira in order that we don&amp;rsquo;t embarrass him.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tetzaveh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh/</guid>
      <description>5782 Pure Olives The Parshah begins ויקחו אליך שמן זית זך. Many people think that שמן זית זך means pure olive oil, the word זך meaning pure and it’s going on שמן. However, the simple explanation, based on the Rishonim, is not like that. On the word זך, Rashi writes בלי שמרים כמו ששנינו במנחות (פו א) מגרגרו בראש הזית וכו&#39;. The Gemara in Menachos says הזית הראשון, מגרגרו בראש הזית which means the olive from the top of the tree was בלי שמרים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terumah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Feb 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah/</guid>
      <description>5782 Necessity of Obligation and Structure for Spritual Life The Parshah begins דבר אל בני ישראל ויקחו לי תרומה מאת כל איש אשר ידבנו לבו תקחו את תרומתי, וזאת התרומה וכו&#39;. In these two Psukim, the word תרומה appears three times. Rashi writes that this alludes to שלש תרומות, three different collections, and he writes the following:
אמרו רבותינו שלש תרומות אמורות כאן, אחת תרומת בקע לגלגלת, שנעשו מהם האדנים, כמו שמפורש באלה פקודי (שמות לח כו - כז), ואחת תרומת המזבח בקע לגלגלת לקופות לקנות מהן קרבנות צבור, ואחת תרומת המשכן נדבת כל אחד ואחד.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mishpatim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jan 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/mishpatim/</guid>
      <description>5782 מרבה בשמחה in Adar Rishon This Shabbos is Shabbos Mevorchim Chodesh Adar Rishon. There is a discussion as to if משנכנס אדר מרבין בשמחה in a leap year applies to Adar Rishon as well or only Adar Sheni. Reb Yaakov Emden in his sefer שו&amp;quot;ת שאילת יעב&amp;quot;ץ ח&amp;quot;ב סי&#39; פ&amp;quot;ח says that it only applies in Adar Sheni. He brings a proof from Rashi in Taanis 29b on משנכנס אדר מרבין בשמחה, Rashi writes משנכנס אדר - ימי נסים היו לישראל: פורים ופסח.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yisro</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yisro/</guid>
      <description>5782 The Reality of the Jewish Experience This week’s Kiddush is sponsored by Simcha Menlo for the Yahrzeit of his grandfather, Mr. Sam Menlo. It is important for Simcha to know that all accomplishments of his grandfather were not self-understood. He wasn’t given anything on a silver platter. He lost his entire family as a young child in the Holocaust, experienced things that are unimaginable, and then came to America with nothing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beshalach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beshalach/</guid>
      <description>5782 The Real You The Parshah begins ויהי בשלח פרעה את העם ולא נחם אלהים דרך ארץ פלשתים כי קרוב הוא כי אמר אלהים פן ינחם העם בראתם מלחמה ושבו מצרימה. ויסב אלהים את העם דרך המדבר ים סוף וכו&#39;. On this Pasuk, the Medrash Rabbah writes ויסב וכו&#39; מכאן אמרו רבותינו אפי&#39; עני שבישראל לא יאכל עד שיסב שכך עשה להם הקדוש ברוך הוא שנאמר ויסב אלהים.
The simple meaning of the word of ויסב is as Rashi writes הסיבם מן הדרך הפשוטה לדרך העקומה that Hashem turned the Jews from the straight forwarded path and took them in a roundabout way.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bo</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Jan 2022 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bo/</guid>
      <description>5782 Nachas Ruach from the struggle The Parshah begins with Hashem telling Moshe בא אל פרעה and the reason is כי אני הכבדתי את לבו. It’s interesting that Moshe is being told to come to Pharaoh-כי-because Hashem hardened his heart. On the contrary, כי אני הכבדתי את לבו would be more of a reason for him not to go to Pharaoh. But it’s possible to translate the word כי as “even if” like is found in Parshas Ki Sisa 34:9 ילך נא אדני בקרבנו כי עם קשה ערף הוא וסלחת לעוננו ולחטאתנו ונחלתנו that כי there means even if.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Va&#39;era</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera/</guid>
      <description>5782 Humble Beginnings The Parshah begins with a discussion between Moshe and Hashem. Hashem tells Moshe to go to Pharaoh and tell him to let the Jews go and Moshe responds that the Jews have not listened and certainly Pharaoh won’t either. In the middle of this dialogue, the Torah deviates and begins talking about the lineage of the Shevatim beginning with Reuven going down to Moshe and Aharon from Levi.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos/</guid>
      <description>5782 Importance of שנים מקרא ואחד תרגום The Parshah begins ואלה שמות בני ישראל (א,א). The Levush in אורח חיים סימן רפה סע&#39; א writes the following:
חייבו חז&amp;quot;ל [ברכות ח ע&amp;quot;א] על כל אדם מישראל שישלים הפרשה בכל שבוע עם הציבור שנים מקרא ואחד תרגום, כדי שיהא בקי בתורה, וסימנך ואל&amp;quot;ה שמו&amp;quot;ת בני ישראל [שמות א, א], ו&amp;rsquo;חייב א&amp;rsquo;דם ל&amp;rsquo;קרות ה&amp;rsquo;פרשה, ש&amp;rsquo;נים מ&amp;rsquo;קרא ו&amp;rsquo;אחד ת&amp;rsquo;רגום, וזה חייבים כל בני ישראל.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayechi</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of the Bar Mitzvah of their son, Akiva Moshe.
Connection of Bar Mitzvah to Parsha This Shabbos is very appropriate for celebrating his Bar Mitzvah not only because it’s actually the week where he is becoming a Bar Mitzvah, but actually because Parshas Vayechi is apropos for a Bar Mitzvah as will be discussed.
(Once a Rebbe came to a village and a Jew came over to him and said Rebbe, in your on honor I’m going to make my son’s Bar Mitzvah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayigash</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash/</guid>
      <description>5781 Approaching One&amp;rsquo;s Self ויגש אליו יהודה ויאמר בי אדני ידבר נא עבדך דבר באזני אדני (מד,יח)
The Parshah begins with Yehuda bringing his case to Yosef. But what exactly was he saying new? He seems to be merely repeating the story that he and Yosef already knew and therefore what caused Yosef to now open up to the brothers?
One thing that Yehuda did add was that he made himself an ערב as the Pasuk says כי עבדך ערב את הנער מעם אבי אם לא אביאנו אליך (מד,לב).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chanukah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chanukah/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Dec 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chanukah/</guid>
      <description>Videos Chanukah 5782 
Chanukah 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miketz</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of Reb Eizel Charif This Shabbos, ד&#39; טבת, is the Yahrzeit of two great people. The first is Reb Yehoshua Isaac Shapiro, who was known as Reb Eizel Charif. He was born in 1801 in the small town of Glubki, near villna and he died in the year 1873. He was a tremendous gaon and very sharp/witty as his name indicates. He was also known for his sharp humor and until today many of his witticism are still known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeshev</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit of the Raavad This Shabbos כ&amp;quot;ו כסלו is the Yahrzeit of the ראב&amp;quot;ד. The Raavad wrote other works but he is most known for his השגות on the Rambam.
The Raavad was Reb Avraham ben Dovid. He is known as the third Raavad. In in Hilchos Lulav (8:5) regarding the Halacha of נקטם by the הדסים writes the following: כבר הופיע רוח הקודש בבית מדרשנו מכמה שנים. Similarly in Hilchos Beis Habchira (6:14) he writes כך נגלה לי מסוד ה&#39; ליראיו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayishlach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach/</guid>
      <description>5782 Jewish Identity Parshas Vayishlach begins with the confrontation between Yaakov and Eisav. This confrontation is really the story of the Jewish people throughout history. The Ramban writes that Reb Yehuda HaNasi would learn Parshas Vayishlach before he dealt with the Romans.
Yaakov wrestles with the שרו של עשו and he says to him הגידה נא שמך and the Malach responds למה זה תשאל לשמי. This could be understood that throughout history, the Jewish people are always trying to fit into a specific society and culture and to blend in.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeitze</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze/</guid>
      <description>5782 Impact of the Departure ויצא יעקב מבאר שבע וילך חרנה
Regarding why the Torah says ויצא and וילך, Rashi writes לא היה צריך לכתוב אלא וילך יעקב חרנה, ולמה הזכיר יציאתו, אלא מגיד שיציאת צדיק מן המקום עושה רושם, שבזמן שהצדיק בעיר הוא הודה הוא זיוה הוא הדרה, יצא משם פנה הודהה פנה זיוה פנה הדרה. It’s not clear what the תועלת is in telling us that יציאת צדיק מן המקום עושה רושם.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toldos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Nov 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos/</guid>
      <description>5782 This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by Mikey Perl in honor of the birth of his daughter Shoshana.
ואלה תולדות This Shabbos is an appropriate Shabbos to celebrate a Kiddush being that the Parshah is about Toldos. There are two Parshiyos that begin with ואלה תולדות. One of them is called Toldos and the other is called Noach. If we don’t want to call two Parshiyos the same name, one would think it would be better to call a Parshah after Yitzchak instead of Noach.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chayei Sara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chayeisara/</guid>
      <description>5782 Chosson Torah The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Eli Rudansky for חתן תורה. A חתן תורה needs to remember that which Chazal say in Kiddushin 41aאמר רב יהודה אמר רב: אסור לאדם שיקדש את האשה עד שיראנה שמא יראה בה דבר מגונה ותתגנה עליו. It must be that if he became a חתן תורה, then he was already יראנה and he knows that it appeals to him. So we want to give a Brachah to the חתן תורה that he should be zocheh that Torah should always be pleasant to him והערב נא ה&#39; אלקינו את דברי תורתך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayera</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera/</guid>
      <description>5781 Haftorah The Haftorah discusses the interaction of Elisha with the wife of Ovadiah and then with the אשה השונמית. The Avudraham and the Levush explain the reason why this Haftorah was chosen for Parshas Vayera is because the second story is about אשה השונמית who had no children and was promised by Elisha that she would have a child. This is מענין הפרשה of Yitzchaks birth which says כעת חיה ולשרה בן and Rashi there explains this is the same expression Elisha uses when promising the אשה השונמית a child.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lech Lecha</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha/</guid>
      <description>5781 Leave Everything Known and Familiar The Parshah begins with Hashem telling Avraham Avinu לך לך מארצך וממולדתך ומבית אביך. Although there are some who are of the opinion that the first נסיון Avraham encountered was the כבשן האש in אור כשדים which is not recorded in the Torah, the אבות דרב נתן and the Rambam in Peirush Hamishnayos אבות פרק חמישי are of the opinion that this command from Hashem was the first of the ten נסיונות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Oct 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach/</guid>
      <description>5780 Celebration of Birth The Kiddush this week was sponsored by the Rossman family in honor of the birth of their daughter.
In Yiddish a למך is a לא יצלח so what did למך, the father of נח, do to have such a name? The Pasuk says the reason why his father named him Noach was because זה ינחמנו ממעשנו ומעצבון ידינו מן האדמה. A person that relies on his children to make a change and a difference in the world and doesn’t take the responsibility upon himself is a real למך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bereishis</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis/</guid>
      <description>5781 Shabbos Breishis This Shabbos is referred to as Shabbos Breishis, as opposed to other Shabbosos that we call it Shabbos Parshas Noach and the like. The Gemara in Baba Basra 121a actually refers to every Shabbos as “Shabbos Breishis” in the context that Shabbos does not require Kiddush Beis Din as opposed to the holidays of the year. However, the Minhag Yisrael is to refer to this Shabbos in particular as Shabbos Breishis which would seem to imply that that with this Shabbos we are beginning something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haazinu</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu/</guid>
      <description>5781 Luchos Shniyos This week we read the Shirah of Haazinu. Rashi along with others learn that the obligation in the Pasuk ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת is referring to Shiras Haazinu. But the Gemara in Sanhedrin 21b learns from that Pasuk the obligation of כתיבה ספר תורה which would seem to mean that השירה הזאת in the Pasuk is referring to כל התורה כולה. The Rambam manages to explain both that really the Shirah in the Pasuk refers to Haazinu, it’s just that one can’t write פרשיות פרשיות and therefore one is required to write the whole Torah so ממילא we see that there is a Mitzvah to write the whole Torah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim Vayelech</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech/</guid>
      <description>Vayelech - 5782 Have Mercy and Be Happy with us We say in the davening on Rosh Hashanah ותשמח במעשיך חמול על מעשיך that Hashem should have compassion and mercy on us and that Hashem should be happy with us. These two statements seem to be a contradiction. We begin saying that we are unworthy when we ask חמול על מעשיך but then we immediately say ותשמח במעשיך to be happy with us, which sounds like we are claiming to be worthy and good people?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yom Kippur</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabbosshuva/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5782 
Thursday Night Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Hashana</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Sep 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshhashana/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5782 
Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
Sicha on Rosh Hashana 5772</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Yemei Elul</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/yemeielul/</guid>
      <description>Videos Motsei Shabbos Slichos 5781 
Thursday Night Shiur 5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Savo</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo/</guid>
      <description>5781 The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Aryeh Leib Reich for the upcoming Yahrzeit of his father.
Death Gives Meaning The Jewish people tend to give more time to commemorating Yahrzeits than to celebrating births. The reason could be because death is really what qualifies living as the Gemara Brachos 5a says יצר הרע מתגבר עליו יזכיר לו יום המיתה. Remembering that life has an end encourages us us to focus on what’s important.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Seitzei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei/</guid>
      <description>5779 Aufruf This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of their sons Aufruf.
The words כי יקח איש אשה appear three times in this week’s Parshah in the following Psukim. כי יקח איש אשה ובא אליה ושנאה (כב,יג)
כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר וכתב לה ספר כריתת ונתן בידה ושלחה מביתו (כד,א)
כי יקח איש אשה חדשה לא יצא בצבא ולא יעבר עליו לכל דבר נקי יהיה לביתו שנה אחת ושמח את אשתו אשר לקח (כד,ה)</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoftim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Kiddush Sponsorship The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Naftali Kasorla in honor of the birth of his daughter, Chava Sheindel.
Adam Harishon named his wife Chava as the Pasuk says ויקרא האדם שם אשתו חוה כי הוא היתה אם כל חי. Rashi says that חוה is from the לשון of חיה. The Baal HaTurim says על שם שמחוה וזהו שאמרו (קידושין מט ב) יו&amp;quot;ד קבין שיחה ירדו לעולם, תשעה נטלו נשים ואחת כל העולם that it’s from a לשון of talking, like it says ולילה ללילה יחוה דעת.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Re&#39;eh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh/</guid>
      <description>5781 Kiddush Sponsorship The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Matisyahu Ginsberger in honor of the birth of a baby boy. Although usually a boy has the bris and a baby girl has a Kiddush, the Baal Simchah felt, due to a variety factors, that the birth of this child warranted an additional Kiddush. Regarding this feeling that was felt by the Baal Simchah, the Rav said over the following Radak.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eikev</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev/</guid>
      <description>5779 Right Mindset The Rebbe Reb Bunim M’Pshichsa would learn Sefer Devarim every day of the year as a mussar sefer because what better mussar sefer could there be than to learn from the mussar of Moshe Rabbeinu. In the beginning of the Parshah, we find two references to יציאת מצרים. They are both two ways of living life and it’s the constant balance that must be kept throughout a person’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vaeschanan</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaeschanan/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaeschanan/</guid>
      <description>5781 Consolation in the Galus The three Shabbasos before Tisha BaAv are called the תלתא דפורענותא because during these Shabosos, we read Haftorahs that talk about the Churban instead of reading a Haftorah which is מענין הפרשה. The seven weeks after Tisha BaAv, beginning with this Shabbos, are known as the שב דנחמתא since the Haftorah of each of these weeks discuss consolation. The תלתא דפורענותא are understandable as we are still in Galus and are still waiting for the building of the Beis Hamikdash.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devarim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim/</guid>
      <description>5781 Blind Spot This Shabbos, ח אב, is the Yahrzeit of the Alter from Kelm. The Rav mentioned that in Kelm, on a Yahrzeit, a Yasom didn’t daven at the Amud. They would say the reason is because the Amud is not a Yasom. (This was prompted by someone in the Shul having Yahrzeit and not davening for the Amud.)
In the Sefer חכמה ומוסר (Volume 2, Siman 71, titled מכל מלמדי השכלתי), the Alter from Kelm writes something that is connected to the beginning of Devarim (1:9-14).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bein HaMitzarim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/beinhamitzarim/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
Thursday Night Shiur 5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matos Masei</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Jul 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos-masei/</guid>
      <description>Matos 5779 Importance of Speech This week’s Parshah begins with the Parshah of Nedarim. Why is it mentioned specifically here, after the episode with Bilaam and Pinchas and between the story with the בנות מדין and the war against מדין?
Rashi in Parshas Balak quotes the Chazal that tells us that Bilaam was given to theאומות העולם as a Navi כדי שלא יהא פתחון פה לאומות לומר אלו היו לנו נביאים חזרנו למוטב (כב,ה).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinchas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 29 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas/</guid>
      <description>5781 Yahrzeit, the Churban, and Moadim The Kiddush was sponsored by Sender Galbut לעלוי נשמת his father, Reb Boruch Tzvi Ben Reuven Nosson Z”L. Dr. Galbut had visited the shul twice when he was already terminally ill and nevertheless he had a captivating smile and radiated Simchah. He was Zocheh that his Yahrzeit be during the ימי המצרים which are anyways days of mourning so he didn’t add another day of sadness.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balak</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak/</guid>
      <description>5780 Chessed Hashem to Connect We begin davening with the Pasuk מה טבו אהלך יעקב משכנתיך ישראל. This Pasuk appears in the Nevuah of Bilaam. However the Maharshal in Tshuvah 64 says not to say this Pasuk because he feels uncomfortable being that it was said by a Rasha such as Bilaam. But according to the understanding that the Pasuk is referring to בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות (סנהדרין קה) (which is why we say it when we walk into shul), it’s a powerful thing that even a Rasha like Bilaam recognized this attribute of Klal Yisrael and therefore all the more so of a reason that it should be included in our davening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chukas</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas/</guid>
      <description>5779 Haftorah This week’s Haftorah discusses יפתח who went to war with בני עמון. The Gemara in ראש השנה דף כה ע&amp;quot;ב says יפתח בדורו כשמואל בדורו. The simple understanding of this Gemara is that in spite of the fact that יפתח was not a prophet and was just a warrior (ילקוט שמעוני ספר שופטים סז goes as far as to say he was not even a בן תורה), nonetheless for his generation he was as good as Shmuel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Korach</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Jun 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach/</guid>
      <description>5781 Motivation for Machlokes The Parsha begins ויקח קרח בן יצהר בן קהת בן לוי ודתן ואבירם בני אליאב ואון בן פלת בני ראובן. This coalition was made up of a group of individuals who were all seeking different things, some the נשיאות and some the כהונה. Although און בן פלת didn’t really have a claim, it could be that he was the man behind the ideological טענה of כל העדה כלם קדשים ובתוכם יקוק ומדוע תתנשאו על קהל ה&#39;.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Meron Tragedy</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/merontragedy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 May 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/merontragedy/</guid>
      <description>In connection with the terrible tragedy that happened in Meron where so many young people, each one special in his own way, were plucked from us in such a quick and cruel way. People have been searching for meaning and therefore we should start with the simple and basic meaning of all this.
The Rav began with a story he heard from his Rebbe Reb Berel Soloveitchik. Reb Chaim Brisker had three sons and the least known was Reb Yisrael Gershon who was a bit eccentric.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lag Baomer</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lagbaomer/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Shiur 5781 
5780</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemini</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemini/</guid>
      <description>Videos Thursday Night Parsha Shiur 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Brachah of Al HaTzadikim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 22 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/alhatzadikim/</guid>
      <description>This Shiur was given to the Beth Jacob community in Atlanta, GA 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inyanei Shovavim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim/</guid>
      <description>This Shmuz was said to the talmidim of Yeshivat HaKotel 5781</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vzos HaBrachah</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vzoshabrachah/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vzoshabrachah/</guid>
      <description>Simultaneously מורשה and מאורסה In the beginning of Vzos Brachah, the Pasuk says תורה צוה לנו משה מורשה קהלת יעקב. Chazal are דורש this Pasuk saying אל תקרי מורשה אלא מאורסה.
But how could it be that Chazal are switching the entire meaning of the Pasuk because מורשה and מאורסה are seemingly diametrically opposed. A מורשה is ירושה and קנינים apply to ירושה because the מעשה קנין is just bringing something that already exists into my ownership, like it says in Behar כי תמכרו ממכר לעמיתך וכו&#39; that the ממכר existed before it was mine.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Chodesh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש. How can we understand this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sukkos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos/</guid>
      <description>5780 The two main mitzvos throughout the Yom Tov of Sukkos are the ארבעה מינים and the סוכה. In the Torah, the Mitzvah of ארבעה מינים is told to us first and a few Psukim later we are commanded to sit in the Sukkah. However, when it comes to מסכת סוכה, the opposite is the case as the first two chapters deal with the Sukkah and only from the third chapter and on does it deal with the ארבעה מינים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayelech</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech/</guid>
      <description>5780 Seudah with Friends This week’s Kiddush was sponsored in honor of the Preidah for R’ Yackov Shwartzbaum. The Rav explained that it’s a סעודת מרעים, where friends get together. The Sefer HaChaim, written by Reb Chaim MVridburg (Brother of the Maharal) in the section titled ספר פרנסה וכלכלה, he writes that a סעודת מרעים, a seudah where people get together in friendship shouldn’t be a small thing in one’s eyes.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lashon Hara</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2016 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/hidabroot/</guid>
      <description>Who Wants Life? 5776</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Search</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/search/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/search/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
