<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>torah on Rav Weinfeld</title>
    <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/tags/torah/</link>
    <description>Recent content in torah on Rav Weinfeld</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://ravweinfeld.com/tags/torah/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Inyanei Shovavim and Va&#39;era 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shovavim_5781/</guid>
      <description>This Shmuz was said to the talmidim of Yeshivat HaKotel</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Va&#39;era 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vaera_5781/</guid>
      <description>Thursday Night Parsha Shiur</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shemos 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 11 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shemos_5781/</guid>
      <description>Yahrzeit of the Rambam  This past week, כ טבת, was the Yahrzeit of the Rambam. He was born in the year 1138 and died in 1204. It’s befitting for his Yahrzeit to fall out the week of Parshas Shemos (the year he died was on the Monday of Shemos like this year) as this is the first Parsha to mention Moshe Rabbeinu. The חסיד יעב&amp;quot;ץ, who lived during the time of the Spanish Inquisition, in his Sefer Ohr HaChaim in the beginning of Perek ט writes אשר כבר נתפרסם על הרמב&amp;quot;ם ממשה עד משה לא קם כמשה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayechi 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Jan 2021 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi_5781/</guid>
      <description>The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of the Bar Mitzvah of their son, Akiva Moshe.
Connection of Bar Mitzvah to Parsha  This Shabbos is very appropriate for celebrating his Bar Mitzvah not only because it’s actually the week where he is becoming a Bar Mitzvah, but actually because Parshas Vayechi is apropos for a Bar Mitzvah as will be discussed. (Once a Rebbe came to a village and a Jew came over to him and said Rebbe, in your on honor I’m going to make my son’s Bar Mitzvah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayigash 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash_5781/</guid>
      <description>ויגש אליו יהודה ויאמר בי אדני ידבר נא עבדך דבר באזני אדני (מד,יח) The Parshah begins with Yehuda bringing his case to Yosef. But what exactly was he saying new? He seems to be merely repeating the story that he and Yosef already knew and therefore what caused Yosef to now open up to the brothers? One thing that Yehuda did add was that he made himself an ערב as the Pasuk says כי עבדך ערב את הנער מעם אבי אם לא אביאנו אליך (מד,לב).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Miketz 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/miketz_5781/</guid>
      <description>This Shabbos, ד&#39; טבת, is the Yahrzeit of two great people. The first is Reb Yehoshua Isaac Shapiro, who was known as Reb Eizel Charif. He was born in 1801 in the small town of Glubki, near villna and he died in the year 1873. He was a tremendous gaon and very sharp/witty as his name indicates. He was also known for his sharp humor and until today many of his witticism are still known.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeshev 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev_5781/</guid>
      <description>This Shabbos כ&amp;quot;ו כסלו is the Yahrzeit of the ראב&amp;quot;ד. The Raavad wrote other works but he is most known for his השגות on the Rambam. The Raavad was Reb Avraham ben Dovid. He is known as the third Raavad. In in Hilchos Lulav (8:5) regarding the Halacha of נקטם by the הדסים writes the following: כבר הופיע רוח הקודש בבית מדרשנו מכמה שנים. Similarly in Hilchos Beis Habchira (6:14) he writes כך נגלה לי מסוד ה&#39; ליראיו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayishlach 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach_5781/</guid>
      <description>ויפל על צוארו וישקהו ויבכו (לג,ד) The Rav said the following vort from his father. Rashi explains why there are נקודות on the word וישקהו. The first opinion is שלא נשקו בכל לבו. The second opinion of רשב&amp;quot;י is הלכה היא בידוע שעשו שונא ליעקב, אלא שנכמרו רחמיו באותה שעה ונשקו בכל לבו. The first explanation is according to the general rule that the נקודות are coming to minimize the meaning of the word that they are on.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeitze 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeitze_5781/</guid>
      <description>The Pasuk in the end of the Parshah says ויעקב הלך לדרכו ויפגעו בו מלאכי אלוקים. Rashi, quoting the Tanchuma, writes מלאכים של ארץ ישראל באו לקראתו ללוותו לארץ. This would seem to indicate that the Malachim went outside of Eretz Yisrael because Yaakov had not yet entered into Eretz Yisrael and the Malachim were already coming to greet him to escort him into Eretz Yisrael. The Ramban asks on Rashi how could this be because we know from the beginning of the Parshah, the Pasuk says והנה מלאכי אלוקים עולים וירדים בו and Rashi says מלאכים שליווהו בארץ אין יוצאים חוצה לארץ ועלו לרקיע וידרדו מלאכי חוצה לארץ ללוותו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Toldos 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/toldos_5781/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins ואלה תולדת יצחק בן אברהם אברהם הוליד את יצחק. As far as the meaning of the word תולדות, there are two opinions in the Rishonim. The Ramban, Ibn Ezra, and Sforno in the beginning of Parshas Noach explain that תולדות mean the “life story of”, and in that context is of Noach and doesn’t necessarily mean children. They support this because the Pasuk in Noach opens up with אלה תולדות נח and doesn’t speak about his children rather it continues נח איש צדיק תמים היה וכו&#39; and only in the next Pasuk does it then list his children.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayera 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Nov 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayera_5781/</guid>
      <description>The Haftorah discusses the interaction of Elisha with the wife of Ovadiah and then with the אשה השונמית. The Avudraham and the Levush explain the reason why this Haftorah was chosen for Parshas Vayera is because the second story is about אשה השונמית who had no children and was promised by Elisha that she would have a child. This is מענין הפרשה of Yitzchaks birth which says כעת חיה ולשרה בן and Rashi there explains this is the same expression Elisha uses when promising the אשה השונמית a child.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lech Lecha 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 31 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha_5781/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with Hashem telling Avraham Avinu לך לך מארצך וממולדתך ומבית אביך. Although there are some who are of the opinion that the first נסיון Avraham encountered was the כבשן האש in אור כשדים which is not recorded in the Torah, the אבות דרב נתן and the Rambam in Peirush Hamishnayos אבות פרק חמישי are of the opinion that this command from Hashem was the first of the ten נסיונות.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bereishis 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Oct 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bereishis_5781/</guid>
      <description>This Shabbos is referred to as Shabbos Breishis, as opposed to other Shabbosos that we call it Shabbos Parshas Noach and the like. The Gemara in Baba Basra 121a actually refers to every Shabbos as “Shabbos Breishis” in the context that Shabbos does not require Kiddush Beis Din as opposed to the holidays of the year. However, the Minhag Yisrael is to refer to this Shabbos in particular as Shabbos Breishis which would seem to imply that that with this Shabbos we are beginning something new.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Haazinu 5781</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu_5781/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/haazinu_5781/</guid>
      <description>This week we read the Shirah of Haazinu. Rashi along with others learn that the obligation in the Pasuk ועתה כתבו לכם את השירה הזאת is referring to Shiras Haazinu. But the Gemara in Sanhedrin 21b learns from that Pasuk the obligation of כתיבה ספר תורה which would seem to mean that השירה הזאת in the Pasuk is referring to כל התורה כולה. The Rambam manages to explain both that really the Shirah in the Pasuk refers to Haazinu, it’s just that one can’t write פרשיות פרשיות and therefore one is required to write the whole Torah so ממילא we see that there is a Mitzvah to write the whole Torah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim Vayelech 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 12 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavimvayelech_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Shabbos before Rosh Hashana is technically Shabbos Mevorchim however for Rosh Chodesh Tishrei, we are not mevarech the Chodesh. The Magen Avrohom says because it says בכסה ליום חגינו and therefore it is to be hidden. The Levush writes the reason is כדי לערבב את השטן. Perhaps another reason is as follows. The Gemara in Megilah 31b explains reason we have the Klalos of Devarim before Rosh Hashanah is כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה and the same is with Brachos as the Gemara says תחל שנה וברכותיה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Savo 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Sep 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisavo_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with the Mitzvah of Bikurim. Last week’s Parshah concludes with remembering Amalek. There is a Machlokes in Yevamos 4a as to whether or not we are דורש סמוכין. But even according to the one who holds we don’t דרשין סמוכין, he agrees that in Mishneh Torah, we are דורש סמוכין. This being the case, what is the connection between the Mitzvah of Bikurim and the Mitzvah of remembering of Amalek?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rosh Chodesh</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/roshchodesh/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש. How can we understand this?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balak 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jul 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak_5780/</guid>
      <description>We begin davening with the Pasuk מה טבו אהלך יעקב משכנתיך ישראל. This Pasuk appears in the Nevuah of Bilaam. However the Maharshal in Tshuvah 64 says not to say this Pasuk because he feels uncomfortable being that it was said by a Rasha such as Bilaam. But according to the understanding that the Pasuk is referring to בתי כנסיות ובתי מדרשות (סנהדרין קה) (which is why we say it when we walk into shul), it’s a powerful thing that even a Rasha like Bilaam recognized this attribute of Klal Yisrael and therefore all the more so of a reason that it should be included in our davening.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Korach 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jun 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach_5780/</guid>
      <description>Rashi begins his commentary on the Parshah by saying פרשה זו יפה נדרשת במדרש רבי תנחומא. The Taz in his sefer Divrei Dovid asks on Rashi that it would seem problematic for Rashi to write such a thing because the Gemara in Eiruvin 64a says כל האומר שמועה זו נאה, וזו אינה נאה - מאבד הונה של תורה and the Gemara proves this from the Pasuk in Mishlei-ורעה זונות יאבד הון.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shelach 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Jun 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with the twelve individuals who were tasked with spying out the land of EY. In describing these men, the Pasuk says איש אחד איש אחד למטה אבתיו תשלחו כל נשיא בהם. If one would read the simple reading of the Pasuk, the words כל נשיא בהם would mean that they sent every Nasi that there was by Jews. But that obviously can’t be, because the Pasuk says איש אחד איש אחד למטה אבתיו תשלחו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaloscha 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Jun 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with Aaron HaKohen being charged with the task of lighting the Menorah. Rashi, quoting the Medrash Tanchuma, asks why is the Parshah of the Menorah juxtaposed to the Parshah of the Nesiim to which he answers לפי שכשראה אהרן חנוכת הנשיאים חלשה דעתו, שלא היה עמהם בחנוכה, לא הוא ולא שבטו, אמר לו הקדוש ברוך הוא חייך, שלך גדולה משלהם, שאתה מדליק ומטיב את הנרות. The fact that the question למה נסמכה is asked indicates that this was not the proper place for the Menorah as we see in the Gemara in Gittin on 60 that the Parshah of the Menorah was given on Rosh Chodesh Nissan before the Nesiim began to bring their Korbanos and not after.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naso 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jun 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso_5780/</guid>
      <description>Our Parshah begins with the different roles of Kehas, Gershon, and Merari. It then goes into the Parsha of Sotah and Nazir and concludes with the קרבנות brought by the נשיאים during the חנוכת המשכן. The question is what do all these things have to do with each other? Rashi brings the Gemara in סוטה ב. That says למה נסמכה פרשת נזיר לפרשת סוטה לומר לך שכל הרואה סוטה בקלקולה יזיר עצמו מן היין.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shavuos</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 May 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shavuos/</guid>
      <description>There is a מנהגin כלל ישראל to put non-bearing fruit trees in shuls on שבועות because on עצרת the judgement for the upcoming year’s fruit tree is decided (מג&amp;quot;א או&amp;quot;ח ס&#39; תצד ס&amp;quot;ק ה). There are two questions that can be asked. Firstly, if we are judged in regard to fruit bearing trees, why do we put non fruit bearing trees in shul? Secondly, why is it that on ט&amp;quot;ו בשבתwhich is ראש השנה לאלנות do we celebrate by eating fruit and not with trees, an on שבועות which we are judged for the upcoming year’s fruit do we celebrate by putting trees in shuls, it should be the opposite?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bamidbar 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 23 May 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/bamidbar_5780/</guid>
      <description>In the end of Sefer Vayikrah, we spoke about counting animals as the Pasuk says וכל מעשר בקר וצאן כל אשר יעבר תחת השבט העשירי יהיה קדש. And now as we begin Parshas Bamidbar, it also begins with counting but it is an entirely different type of counting as the Pasuk says במספר שמות. But the phrase במספר שמות is confusing because on the one hand were counting just numbers, but on the other hand we are counting שמות as if to say you have a name and unique qualities and a distinction?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Sisa 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Mar 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kisisa_5780/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by Reb Yisrael Neuberger in honor of his new book “Hold On”. (On the cover, there is a rope so the Rav digressed on the idea of a חבל.) The word חבל not only means a rope but at times is used to describe a גרל as the Pasuk says in Haazinu כי חלק יקוק עמו יעקב חבל נחלתו( לב,ט). Now if every creation and creature in this world has a specific purpose as it says לא ברא הקב&amp;quot;ה דבר אחד לבטלה (במ&amp;quot;ר יח,יח, זהר א כג), then all the more so, the human being which is created בצלם אלוקים for sure has a purpose and a mission that only he can fulfil.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Purim</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 08 Mar 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/purim/</guid>
      <description>Haman thought that Adar was a month of bad luck for the Jews because of the death of Moshe and it was probably a painful and difficult day for the Jews being that they lost the greatest leader in history. But the Jews pulled it together and on that day they learned a very important lesson. They learned that as a people we must keep moving on and with the death comes a new beginning and opportunity.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Tetzaveh Zachor 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Mar 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/tetzaveh_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Mitzvah of זכירת עמלק is not just to incite the שנאה towards the people of Amalek but towards the evil aspect that which they represent, as the Maggid from Koznitz says that every Jew needs to eradicate the Amalek, that which it embodies and personifies, from within. There have been many enemies of the Jews in our history but we are only commanded to remember that which Amalek in order to not lose the שנאה over generations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Terumah 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Feb 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/terumah_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Reb Shalom Huss in honor of his father’s Yahrzeit. Adar is the month that is very much connected to Yahrzeits. Although Ahron Hakohen’s Yahrzeit is recorded in the Torah, it’s Moshe Rabbeinu’s Yahrzeit that is the focus. The Chevra Kadisha picked ז&#39; אדר, the Yahrzeit of Moshe Rabbeinu, as the universal day for dealing with death and burial. Haman thought that Adar was a month of bad luck for the Jews because of the death of Moshe and it was probably a painful and difficult day for the Jews being that they lost the greatest leader in history.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayechi 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Jan 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayechi_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Kiddush this week was sponsored by the Orenstein family in memory of their uncle. Why do Jews commemorate Yartzeits but we don’t celebrate birthdays? There are two פרשיות in the Torah which talk about people dying and we call them חיי שרה and ויחי, indicating life and not death. The reason is because only once a person is no longer alive can we really evaluate his life. But while a person is still alive and his life is still in the making, it’s difficult to really evaluate a person’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayigash 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Jan 2020 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayigash_5780/</guid>
      <description>ויגש אליו יהודה ויאמר בי אדני ידבר נא עבדך דבר באזני אדני (מד,יח) The Parshah begins with Yehuda bringing his case to Yosef and uses the word ויגש that Yehuda approached. When it comes to the completion of Shemona Esreih, we take three steps backwards which is מדינא דגמרא. But the earliest source we have for the three steps forward that we take at the beginning of Shemona Esreih is from the רוקח brought down by the רמ&amp;quot;א ס&#39; צה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayeshev 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 20 Dec 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayeshev_5780/</guid>
      <description>After the incident of מכירת יוסף, the Torah interrupts with the story of Yehuda and Tamar, which begins with Yehuda going to find a wife. On the Pasuk ויט עד איש עדולמי וכו&#39;, the Medrash says the following: רב שמואל בר נתן פתח (ירמיה כט) כי אנכי ידעתי את המחשבות, שבטים היו עסוקים במכירת יוסף ויוסף עסוק בשקו ובתענותיו וכו&#39; ויהודה עסק ליקח אשה והקב&amp;quot;ה היה עוסק ובורא אורה של משיח.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayishalch 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Dec 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayishlach_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Parshah begins with Yaakov sending מלאכים to Eisav. Rashi explains on the words וישלח יעקב מלאכים that they were מלאכים ממש, to tell us they were angles and not human messengers. However, if the word מלאך also means messenger (being the word “angel” comes from the Greek word “angelos” which means messenger), then how does saying מלאכים ממש tell us they were angels, if it just translates as real ממש)) messengers?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lech Lecha 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 09 Nov 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/lechlecha_5780/</guid>
      <description>Unless a person prepares beforehand, he won’t gain all there is to gain from the Haftarah of that week. (Here, The Rav went off on a side point regarding davening. With Hebrew not being the first language for most of us, people don’t appreciate the nuances and the music. When it comes to davening as well, we don’t appreciate the words and their music it sings and therefore some add their own music to them.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Noach 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Nov 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/noach_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Kiddush this week was sponsored by the Rossman family in honor of the birth of their daughter.
 In Yiddish a למך is a לא יצלח so what did למך, the father of נח, do to have such a name? The Pasuk says the reason why his father named him Noach was because זה ינחמנו ממעשנו ומעצבון ידינו מן האדמה. A person that relies on his children to make a change and a difference in the world and doesn’t take the responsibility upon himself is a real למך.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sukkos 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/sukkos_5780/</guid>
      <description>The two main mitzvos throughout the Yom Tov of Sukkos are the ארבעה מינים and the סוכה. In the Torah, the Mitzvah of ארבעה מינים is told to us first and a few Psukim later we are commanded to sit in the Sukkah. However, when it comes to מסכת סוכה, the opposite is the case as the first two chapters deal with the Sukkah and only from the third chapter and on does it deal with the ארבעה מינים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabboscholhamoedsukkos_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shabboscholhamoedsukkos_5780/</guid>
      <description>The Brachos for the Haftorah on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos are different than on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Pesach. On Shabbos Chol Hamoed Pesach, there is no mention of Pesach in Brachah על התורה nor does it end with מקדש השבת וישראל והזמנים. However, on Shabbos Chol Hamoed Sukkos, there is mention of חג הסוכות and it ends with מקדש השבת וישראל והזמנים. How could this be understood? A possible explanation could be as follows.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Vayelech 5780</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech_5780/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/vayelech_5780/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Kiddush was sponsored in honor of the Preidah for R’ Yackov Shwartzbaum. The Rav explained that it’s a סעודת מרעים, where friends get together. The Sefer HaChaim, written by Reb Chaim MVridburg (Brother of the Maharal) in the section titled ספר פרנסה וכלכלה, he writes that a סעודת מרעים, a seudah where people get together in friendship shouldn’t be a small thing in one’s eyes. Because it’s not for nothing that Chazal said that people shouldn’t break for Tefilah when they are involved in such a seudah because such a seudah is a big deal and is somewhat an expression of Tefilah, that which people nourish the אהבה between themselves.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Nitzavim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/nitzavim_5779/</guid>
      <description>The Gemara in מגילה דף לא ע&amp;quot;ב says that Ezra established that we should read the קללות in Vayikra before Shavuos and the קללות of Devarim before Rosh Hashanah כדי שתכלה שנה וקללותיה. It’s not merely because we finish the torah once a year that the קללות fall out near Rosh Hashanah rather its part of the Takana of Ezra, and even בני מערבא who competed the Torah in three years would read the קללות around Rosh Hashanah being it’s relevant for the time period.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ki Seitzei 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 14 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/kiseitzei_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Kiddush was sponsored by the Feldinger family in honor of their sons Aufruf.
 The words כי יקח איש אשה appear three times in this week’s Parshah in the following Psukim. כי יקח איש אשה ובא אליה ושנאה (כב,יג) כי יקח איש אשה ובעלה והיה אם לא תמצא חן בעיניו כי מצא בה ערות דבר וכתב לה ספר כריתת ונתן בידה ושלחה מביתו (כד,א) כי יקח איש אשה חדשה לא יצא בצבא ולא יעבר עליו לכל דבר נקי יהיה לביתו שנה אחת ושמח את אשתו אשר לקח (כד,ה) In fact, the source for כסף קדושין is learned out from the גזירה שוה of קיחה קיחה משדה עפרון and one of them is in the Parshah.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shoftim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 07 Sep 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shoftim_5779/</guid>
      <description>The end of the Parshah deals with the עגלה ערופה. The Pasuk says ויצאו זקניך ושפטיך. Rashi says the זקניך are the סנהדרין גדולה. Every time a dead body was found, the entire Sanhedrin would have to get up from Jerusalem and travel to wherever the body was found. The question is who the beheaded heifer is coming to represent. One could have thought that it represents the murderer as the Pasuk says in the end of Parshas Masei ולארץ לא יכפר לדם אשר שפך בה כי אם בדם שפכו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reeh 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/reeh_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Rosh Chodesh Elul. One would think that when comparing the two, Shabbos is greater than Rosh Chodesh. However, from the Gemara in זבחים דף צא ע&amp;quot;א it appears that Rosh Chodesh is greater and more holy because the Gemara wants to prove that תדיר precedes מקודש because the musafei Shabbos come before the musafei Rosh Chodesh which is תדיר even though Rosh Chodesh is more מקודש.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Eikev 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 24 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/eikev_5779/</guid>
      <description>The Rebbe Reb Bunim M’Pshichsa would learn Sefer Devarim every day of the year as a mussar sefer because what better mussar sefer could there be than to learn from the mussar of Moshe Rabbeinu. In the beginning of the Parshah, we find two references to יציאת מצרים. They are both two ways of living life and it’s the constant balance that must be kept throughout a person’s life.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Devarim 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/devarim_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week is Shabbos Chazon. The רמ&amp;quot;א סימן תקנא paskens that one should not wear בגדי שבת on Shabbos Chazon. The Mishnah Berura writes that in Vilna, they hold like the Gra and therefore they wear Shabbos clothing. However he is hesitant, and says that at least one garment should not be from בגדי שבת. But today everybody wears Shabbos clothing without a question. How could this be explained? The Rav suggested based on the מהרי&amp;quot;ל that says the reason we don’t wear Shabbos clothing on Shabbos Chazon even though there is a potential issue of אבילות בפרהסיא is because an onlooker who sees someone not wearing Shabbos clothing might assume that he doesn’t have any Shabbos clothing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Masei 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/masei_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Aug 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/masei_5779/</guid>
      <description>We say in the ברכות מעין שלש the words ונאכל מפריה ונשבע מטובה ונברך עליה בקדשה ובטהרה. The Poskim (See טור סימן רח) want to remove the words ונאכל מפריה ונשבע מטובה because of the Gemara in Sotah 14a. The Gemara there says as follows: דרש רבי שמלאי מפני מה נתאוה משה רבינו ליכנס לא&amp;quot;י וכי לאכול מפריה הוא צריך או לשבוע מטובה הוא צריך אלא כך אמר משה הרבה מצות נצטוו ישראל ואין מתקיימין אלא בא&amp;quot;י אכנס אני לארץ כדי שיתקיימו כולן על ידי The Gemara seems to indicate that it would be wrong if Moshe’s desire to enter EY was in order to eat the fruits and therefore gives another suggestion as to why Moshe desired to enter the land.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matos 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/matos_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Parshah begins with the Parshah of Nedarim. Why is it mentioned specifically here, after the episode with Bilaam and Pinchas and between the story with the בנות מדין and the war against מדין? Rashi in Parshas Balak quotes the Chazal that tells us that Bilaam was given to theאומות העולם as a Navi כדי שלא יהא פתחון פה לאומות לומר אלו היו לנו נביאים חזרנו למוטב (כב,ה). The emphasis is on the פה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pinchas 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 27 Jul 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/pinchas_5779/</guid>
      <description>People say that sometimes חקת and בלק are together and sometimes they are separate, as are מטות and, מסעי but פנחס is always by itself because the קנאי is always by himself. קנאות is a word that is one of the most misused terms in Jewish life. Because if you look in the Mishna in סנהדרין צא ע&amp;quot;א you see that there are only four things that we say קנאין are פוגעין בו and the הלכה is אין מורין לו.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Balak 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 20 Jul 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/balak_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week there was an Aufruf and this is what was said over. We’re going to give only a ברכה, and were going to give a ברכה in spite of the fact that the Mishna in Avos says to be talmidim of אברהם and not talmidim of בלעם. But even if were are not talmidim of בלעם, we should still be able to learn something from him also as Chazal say איזהו חכם הלומד מכל אדם.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Chukas 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Jul 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/chukas_5779/</guid>
      <description>This week’s Haftorah discusses יפתח who went to war with בני עמון. The Gemara in ראש השנה דף כה ע&amp;quot;ב says יפתח בדורו כשמואל בדורו. The simple understanding of this Gemara is that in spite of the fact that יפתח was not a prophet and was just a warrior (ילקוט שמעוני ספר שופטים סז goes as far as to say he was not even a בן תורה), nonetheless for his generation he was as good as Shmuel.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Korach 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Jun 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/korach_5779/</guid>
      <description>The past few פרשיות, Rashis opening line has been למה נסמכה. Seemingly because the events that were being mentioned were not in the chronological order, and therefore there needed to be a logic to the order. However, when it comes to Korach, Rashi does not ask למה נסמכה. Therefore, it must be that this is the right place chronologically for the story with Korach. This is reinforced by what Rashi says on the Pasuk ויפלו על פניו, the reason being because this was the סרחון רביעי, the third being the חטא המרגלים.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shelach 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 24 Jun 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/shelach_5779/</guid>
      <description>In the middle of last week’s פרשה, the Jews were getting ready to enter into ארץ ישראל. Moshe was trying to convince יתרו to join them, as he says נוסעים אנחנו אל המקום. The only thing the Jews were afraid of was external enemies, as the Pasuk says ויפצו איביך וינסו משנאך מפניך. But the real problem was internally, as the following Pasuk says ויהי העם כמתאוננים. The Pasuk doesn’t even state what they were complaining about, and its only Rashi who explains what they were complaining about.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Behaloscha 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 16 Jun 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/behaloscha_5779/</guid>
      <description>What is the significance of the Shabbos after Shavuos? We say in the song כל מקדש שביעי the words המאחרים לצאת מן השבת וממהרים לבוא. The question is why is it in that order? The verse should first say we are ממהר לבוא , regarding bringing in Shabbos, and then say מאחר לצאת מן השבת, regarding concluding Shabbos, so why do we say it in this order? The Rav wanted to suggest that תוספת שבת only began from after מתן תורה.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Naso 5779</title>
      <link>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso_5779/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 14 Jun 2019 11:30:03 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ravweinfeld.com/posts/naso_5779/</guid>
      <description>The Kiddush this Shabbos was sponsored by Kobe Schwarzbaum. Schwarzbaum means black tree in Yiddish so from that, the Rav went on to talking about trees.
 There is a מנהגin כלל ישראל to put non-bearing fruit trees in shuls on שבועות because on עצרת the judgement for the upcoming year’s fruit tree is decided (מג&amp;quot;א או&amp;quot;ח ס&#39; תצד ס&amp;quot;ק ה). There are two questions that can be asked. Firstly, if we are judged in regard to fruit bearing trees, why do we put non fruit bearing trees in shul?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
